<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Catechizing Gods ordinance: or A short treatise concerning that [brace] ancient approved soul-edifying singularly necessary [brace] exercise of catechizing. Delivered in sundry sermons at Botolphs Aldgate, London. / By Zach. Crofton minister of the word.</title>
            <author>Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 86 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80842</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6990</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1665_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208381</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867336</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867336</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119643</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80842)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119643)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 209:E1665[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Catechizing Gods ordinance: or A short treatise concerning that [brace] ancient approved soul-edifying singularly necessary [brace] exercise of catechizing. Delivered in sundry sermons at Botolphs Aldgate, London. / By Zach. Crofton minister of the word.</title>
                  <author>Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 132, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Cotes for Tho. Parkhurst, at the Three Crowns over against the great conduit at the lower end of Cheapside,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Final leaf = advertisment.</note>
                  <note>"Ancient .. necessary" are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 25.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Catechetics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119643:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Catechizing Gods Ordinance: OR A SHORT TREATISE CONCERNING That
<list>
                  <item>Ancient</item>
                  <item>Approved</item>
                  <item>Soul-edifying</item>
                  <item>Singularly neceſſary</item>
               </list> Exerciſe of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizing.</p>
            <p>DELIVERED In ſundry SERMONS at <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolphs Aldgate, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Zach. Crofton</hi> Miniſter of the Word.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Jeſus Chriſt in his childhood ſubmitted himſelf to this Ordinance of God, though he were repleniſhed with all divine wiſdome. <bibl>
                     <hi>Downam of Catech. p. 334.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Knowledge of the Word is as neceſſary an art for Chriſtians, as the art of husbandry is neceſſary for husbandmen. <bibl>
                     <hi>Greenh. p. 383.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Inviſa poſſumus cupere, incognita nequaquam. <bibl>
                     <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Train up a childe in the way he ſhould go, and when he is old he will not depart from it. <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 22.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Whom ſay ye that I am? ſome ſay <hi>Elias,</hi> ſome <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> ſome <hi>Jeremiah</hi> or one of the Prophets. Whom ſay ye that I am? Thou art Chriſt the Son of the living God. <bibl>
                     <hi>Mat. 16.13, 14, 15, 16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. Cotes</hi> for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Three Crowns</hi> over againſt the great Conduit at the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119643:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119643:2"/>
            <head>To his much honoured and truly endeared in the Lord, the Chriſtian Inhabitants within the Pariſh of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolphs</hi> without <hi>Aldgate,</hi> as well without as within the Liberty of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Endeared in the Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Preſent to the view of you all, what hath been plainly preached to the ears of ſuch whoſe hearts God hath inclined to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend on my publick Miniſtry. It is the chief and plain heads of
<pb facs="tcp:119643:3"/>ſundry Sermons without all Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit-repetitions, which would have ſwelled the volume too much; and without all flouriſhes of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſentences and citation of Authors, which might have made it nauſeous to the mindes of ſuch who judge <hi>things goodneſſe by their pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nneſſe:</hi> the main ſcope and drift of it is to vindicate <hi>the dignity</hi> of a deſpiſed, and <hi>due au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> of a denied <hi>Ordinance of God;</hi> to revive in the Church an anciently exerciſed; and too too long exil'd <hi>priviledge;</hi> to excite and quicken to that too too long <hi>neglected duty</hi> of <hi>Catechizing</hi> in all Chriſtian ſocieties. This work I confeſſe hath been done by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more able and eminent Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Church, as holy Mr. <hi>Greenham,</hi> reverend Mr. <hi>Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,</hi> acute Mr. <hi>Forde,</hi> and the reverend <hi>Provincial Aſſembly</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:119643:3"/>the Churches of God within the City and Province of <hi>London;</hi> many times I had it in my thoughts to have commended theſe to your reading, but fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what in that caſe I ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire might paſſe in at one ear and out at another; and I being by ſome deſired, and by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince enjoyned to preach on the nature of this duty; and having calculated the doctrine for your condition and capacity, thought it might moſt ſure with you to put my own digeſted conſiderations into your hands; the which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be the more welcome to ſuch whoſe ears heard them, and whoſe hearts were touched in the publique delivery: the acceptance of them by ſuch is not to be doubted; and by all others it is deſired, that they may be ſo farre accepted as to be taken up, read
<pb facs="tcp:119643:4"/>without paſſion or prejudice; the Doctrine therein taught may be revolved in your deliberate thoughts; and prayer may be put up to the God of Wiſdome, to open your eyes unto the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion and acknowledgement of the truth: This acceptance is the rather deſired, for that</p>
            <p n="1">1. This little Tract is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to you as a taſte of that pity, and teſtimony of that true affection I bear to you in the Lord, <hi>as your Miniſter:</hi> againſt which though I ſtrongly reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, yet providence hath ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that after all the ſad changes, and Religion-ruining revolutions, to which the times have ſubjected you, you are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to my care and charge, and I hope I can unfeignedly ſay, you are now my <hi>Dearly beloved and much longed for in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119643:4"/>
            <p n="2">2. This Tract travels in this publick way to ſeek out them, who by reaſon of the ſpirit of deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and prophaneneſſe, withdraw their ears from hearing it when preached; I thought it a duty to preach to the eyes of them whoſe ears are ſhut to ſuch abſolute <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion-preſerving ordinances,</hi> as this is of <hi>Catechizing.</hi> I hope you have more <hi>charity</hi> then to ſuffer a <hi>Pariſh Childe</hi> born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you to paſs by your houſes without one nights, nay a few hours entertainment: and I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire none may appear ſo <hi>cruel,</hi> as to ſpurn and kick it out of their houſes <hi>for the fathers ſake,</hi> and the rather for that the father is to be found ready to traverſe all inditements againſt himſelf or doctrine, if he may but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy a patient hearing; but in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial take heed that none <hi>look
<pb facs="tcp:119643:5"/>aſquint</hi> at it, and <hi>carry doggedly</hi> towards it for propounding <hi>a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and pleading for <hi>a piece of piety,</hi> for therein they engage the God of wiſdome and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to plead his own cauſe. As for ſuch as ſhall be ready to flight it on a ſeeming <hi>ſcrupuloſity</hi> of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience concerning the novelty, or antiquity, or formality, &amp;c. of the exerciſe for which it contends, I deſire they will with patience read it through, it may be the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve of their ſcruples may make them more eſteem it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The duty herein preſſed, is that which concerns you all of what ever age or condition: Are you <hi>ignorant?</hi> Catechizing is the way to knowledge; and certainly, knowledge in rudiments of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, is an abſolute duty incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent on every man, be he rich or poor, high or low, young or old.
<pb facs="tcp:119643:5"/>It is a very good obſervation the Provinciall Aſſembly have in their exhortation to the ſame duty, and I deſire you may well note it, it is this:</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">It is the rare priviledge of the Romiſh Synagogue to have ſuch a power over ignorance, as to command her to imploy her ſelf as a tender nurſe to their blind devotions; but the Church of Chriſt hath ever found her ſuch a froward piece, as that ſhe hath churliſhly handled all the genuine iſſues of truth &amp; piety; and as fondly cockered all the mis-ſhapen monſters of error, though never ſo ſtrangely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of an heterogeneous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixture of ſuperſtition and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe.</q> And as they, I muſt needs ſay, we cannot nouriſh our ſelves with the leaſt hope as to ſee ignorance become ſerviceable to
<pb facs="tcp:119643:6"/>true piety: we know the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons cannot outgo the apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of truth, till ſhe be known, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be reverenced, cannot but be hated.</p>
            <p>Are you <hi>knowing?</hi> yet Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing concerns you not only in that thereby you communicated knowledge to others (according to your duty) but alſo the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm is to you no leſſe uſefull then the compaſſe to the moſt skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Mariner, to ſteer your courſe with <hi>method and order</hi> in theſe boiſterous daies of confuſed noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as a touchſtone to the moſt diſcerning Goldſmith to try me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, and detect the moſt glitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring falſities that are ſpread before you with a <hi>Chriſt, Chriſt,</hi> as a rule to the moſt underſtanding Architect, by which you ſquare your actions in the ſpirituall edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of your immortall ſouls.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119643:6"/>
            <p>Are you <hi>poor?</hi> Catechizing is a very cheap and eaſie way, in a few hours time, in two pence ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence to make you rich in faith.</p>
            <p>Are you <hi>rich?</hi> Religion will make you <hi>civill,</hi> literature will be your <hi>honour,</hi> and none ſo much as <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> which will be the very glory of a Princes Crown.</p>
            <p>Nay not only doth the duty preſſed, but the very preſſing of it concern you all; and that in order to the quickning of your lukewarm ſpirits, convincing your very conſciences of <hi>a duty to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techize</hi> and <hi>be Catechized:</hi> Hath not the long neglect of this exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe to ſome, loſt the divine ſtamp of it, and armed young men (when called to Catechizing) with impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to call its <hi>authority</hi> into queſtion? how many ſtick not to call it an <hi>humane invention?</hi> how many others account it <hi>good,</hi> but
<pb facs="tcp:119643:7"/>
               <hi>not neceſſary;</hi> allow it where it is uſed, but live without the diſcharge of it themſelves, as if it concerned not them? if ever it had need to be preſſed now with moſt power and plainneſſe, pregnant and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive arguments; the youth of this age <hi>through want of Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing,</hi> are captivated with <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and Schiſm;</hi> and if the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect be continued, the youth of the next will be capable of turning <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan</hi> or <hi>Papiſt;</hi> but in the paſt ages of the Churches by this very means, as you have heard and may read, young children were prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for Martyrdome in the defence of their Religion.</p>
            <p>If any enquire and wonder that I preach and preſent to your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo low, plain, common, and ordinary Doctrines in this high flown, wiſe and knowing age: <hi>I deſire ſuch to know,</hi> I am not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible
<pb facs="tcp:119643:7"/>that the age in which we live, is <hi>an age of comforts,</hi> and that the now great enquiry of our Saints is after <hi>joy, not duty; aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, not aſſent of faith;</hi> but truly I ſtudy not what may <hi>pleaſe you,</hi> but what may <hi>profit you;</hi> the practiſes of holineſſe in Word, Sacraments, and Sabbaths, are more for your profit then the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of a Chriſtian: and whileſt your heads are lifted ſo high, that you tread and trample under your feet the <hi>principles and poſitive duties</hi> (pearls of no ſmall value) it is high time to ſet the luſtre of them before your eyes, and to make wantons know ſweet meats were not intended to work a contempt of common and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary food: and again, you have been too long <hi>pleaſed</hi> and puffed up with <hi>high flown doctrines:</hi> nay and the ſpirituall riches under
<pb facs="tcp:119643:8"/>which you travell (I mean that heady diſorderly knowledge, ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in free, but very confuſed diſcourſes) makes me very jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous they were not wholſome. Laſtly, I have cauſe to fear that generally you cannot yet <hi>bear higher Doctrine;</hi> if God will, I ſhall leave the firſt rudiments, and go on towards perfection, when I have firſt laid the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, you will do well to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider ſome men (who deſire to make the bounds of Chriſt his Church narrower then the Lord hath ſet them) hath under the notions of gathering Churches, ſtirred you in many parts and private congregations, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>churched (as much as in them lies) your whole bodies holding the place of a publick Miniſter, but neither owned nor diſcharged the duties thereof <hi>in your inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119643:8"/>nor yet giving way for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to do it: nay, nor yet have they inſtructed the poor ſouls ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into their ſocieties: great is the ignorance in foundation principles I finde, and greater I fear amongſt you; nor, when I conſider how it hath been with you, do I wonder; but only this I ſay, how ſhall they be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the comforts that flow from the enjoyment of Chriſt, that are yet to be convinced that Chriſt is <hi>preſent to every beleever in the Sacrament, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by way of efficacy, but alſo of reall exiſtency,</hi> yet not corporall in a Popiſh ſenſe. But I will hold you no longer at the threſhold; the Doctrine I have preached to ſome, and printed for all, I tender it to you as a <hi>Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> nay, as <hi>your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119643:9"/>ſet over you by the Lord, and watching for your ſouls, and deſirous to give up my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of you with joy, and not with grief, as ſuch and I, this ſmall Tract ſo tendred, I beſeech you, nay I charge you in the Lord, receive both <hi>me</hi> and <hi>it.</hi> I am not ignorant that ſome amongſt you who are ready to deny the <hi>exiſtency of Goſpel Miniſtry,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe it as <hi>Antichriſtian;</hi> deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine <hi>the cry of holineſſe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ordination,</hi> and the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry to lie ſo common, that <hi>any man may</hi> (though to them none muſt) <hi>be manifeſt;</hi> and are ſo farre from ſubjecting, that they ſet themſelves over others, bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Catechizing the Catechizers,</hi> will be ready to diſclaim and deny any ſubjection or relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to me, and diſpute my au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb facs="tcp:119643:9"/>as a Miniſter: But to ſuch I ſay the Fathers authority is better exerciſed then debated amongſt froward children. I have offered openly and do offer again to give to the ſober diſſatisfied ſoul (that will with patience and meekneſſe hear) full ſatisfaction, not only concerning this, but all other principles, of which this Scepticall age hath cauſed them to doubt: I may not now ſtand to anſwer further, but invite them home, and in the mean time ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the duty preſſed to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, Catechizing to be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to your Families and Schools, your children and ſervants to be duly preſented when called to this duty in the Church: and fervent prayers for a bleſſing upon it and upon me, that God would enable me to doe the work
<pb facs="tcp:119643:10"/>which concernes your everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting welfare; which is, and by Gods grace ſhall be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely and fervently followed by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The meaneſt of the Lords Labourers for your Souls ſalvation,<hi>Zach. Crofton.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:119643:10"/>
            <head>The Contents</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IN this Treatiſe you have diſcuſſed this Doctrine:</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Catechizing is Gods Ordinance, very uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to his Church,</hi> pag. 11</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The word Catechize explained, and the thing deſcribed,</hi> p. 1, 2, 3</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The reaſons that enforce the Doctrine, and they are drawn from its</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Excellency in reſpect of its</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Preſcriber, God,</hi> p. 15</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Profeſſors, Saints,</hi> p. 17</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Prime matter,</hi> p. 19</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Proper end,</hi> p. 20</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Antiquity,</hi> p. 21</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> p. 28</item>
                     <item>4. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tility, in that it</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. <hi>Preſerves Religion in purity,</hi> p. 31</item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Propagates to poſterity,</hi> p. 35</item>
                           <item>3. <hi>Prepares for increaſe of Knowledge in Chriſt,</hi> p. 36</item>
                           <item>4. <hi>Profits by the Word,</hi> p. 37</item>
                           <item>5. <hi>Prevents Apoſtaſie,</hi> p. 38</item>
                           <item>6. <hi>Preſents fit Communicants to the Lords Supper,</hi> p. 41</item>
                           <item>7. <hi>Powerfully diſpoſeth to duty,</hi> p. 45</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119643:11"/>
                     <item>5. <hi>Eaſineſſe and familiarity,</hi> p. 46</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The proper matter about which Catechizing is converſant,</hi> p. 47</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The formes to be uſed and manner how it is to be managed,</hi> p. 57</item>
               <item>Under which is noted thoſe that muſt Catechize;
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Miniſters in their Congregations,</hi> p. 60</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Schoolmaſters in their Schools,</hi> p. 65</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Maſters of Families in their Families,</hi> p. 70</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>All that are ignorant, and in ſpeciall youth, and why they muſt be Catechized, &amp; how they muſt carry in ſubjecting to it,</hi> p 78</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The Doctrine applyed.</head>
               <item>1. <hi>To inform of the neceſſity and dignity of Catechizing,</hi> p. 86</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Reproof of Superiors neglect,</hi> p. 93
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Inferiors not ſubmiſſion,</hi> p. 110</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To exhort to the duty, which exhortation is enforced with ſeverall motives,</hi> p. 125</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 7. <hi>for</hi> them <hi>read</hi> then, <hi>p.</hi> 27. <hi>lin.</hi> 21. <hi>r.</hi> Canons of the Councels at, <hi>p.</hi> 32. <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>r.</hi> Cookes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:119643:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119643:12"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edm. Calamy.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119643:12"/>
            <head>To the Reverend the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Aſſembly of the Churches of God within the City and Province of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Fathers and Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Edications of Books, and inſcriptions of the names of men of worth and honour, are grown ſo common, that the plaineſt Truths and meaneſt Tracts diſcuſsing the ſame, cannot paſſe without them, and thereby a craved and enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged patronage: if this ſmall Tract of ſo plain a duty muſt ſeek any, for many conſiderable reaſons, it
<pb facs="tcp:119643:13"/>muſt ſeek you, and none but your ſelves, as its Patrons.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> That the Author may hereby teſtifie to the world and your ſelvef his thankfull acknowledgement<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> os Gods great mercy to his Church, not only for <hi>your being in theſe times of envie and indignation at all Church order and authority;</hi> but alſo for your <hi>vigilancy over, and induſtry for the good of the Churches of God,</hi> eminently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved not only in your elaborate <hi>vindications of Government and Miniſtry,</hi> but alſo in your late grave, ſerious, and authoritative <hi>exhortation unto Catechizing;</hi> wherein by many pregnant and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive reaſons, you do provoke Miniſters as well as others to a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the long neglect of which, with its ſad effects, is to us in the ſight of God and his Church, matter of ſhame and ſorrow.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119643:13"/>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> To you it is directed as authors of its reſurrection, though not firſt being, though at my firſt coming into your City (in the purſuit of the duty) I did ſome years ſince preach it to the people of whom I had the inſpection,
<note place="margin">At <hi>James Garlick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hithe.</hi>
               </note> yet I had laid it by me as dead, and determined it ſhould never ſee the light, nor ſound in the ears of men any more; yet the ſound of your exhorting trumpet put again life into it, and cauſed it to be preached to a more publick audience for the benefit of a much greater people, to all whoſe ears the ſound not reaching, I was conſtrained to make it thus pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, that by reading what they ſhould have heard, they might be convinced of, and counſelled unto duty; and now it is cheerfully ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to your cenſure, at whoſe command it was preached, though not the firſt yet the ſecond time.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119643:14"/>
            <p>To you it comes in obedience to your command and conformity to your order, which requires <hi>an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to be given from the ſeveral Claſſes of what proceeding is made in the work of Catechizing,</hi> to which you exhort; let this ſmall Tract aſſure you of the chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſubmiſſion of the meaneſt of your brethren to your exhortation, and full reſolution to revive that ordinance of <hi>Catechizing,</hi> ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, uſefull, and advantagious to the Church of God; prefeſsing that the greateſt comfort that ever my ſoul enjoyed in all my mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriall endevours amongſt the people with whom I lately la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured,
<note place="margin">James Garlick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hithe.</note> was in the inſtruction and (ſo far as I and others of their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian acquaintance can judge) ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f ſome young men and young women, that did with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and diligence, againſt all
<pb facs="tcp:119643:14"/>diſcouragements ſubmit unto and ſtudy their Catechiſm.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, To your patronage it is commended, for that your exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the duty preſſed in it, and purſued by it; gives the Author full aſſurance of your readineſſe to patronize it, and by your power to protect it againſt the common car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and cavillers at every truth and duty, with which our age a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds, and with the clemency that becomes your aſſembly, indulge the infirmities of its author in the weak management of ſo weighty a matter.</p>
            <p>Having given you the reaſons of my boldneſſe in this Dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I muſt crave leave to apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gize in one thing, my not comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with your exhorting directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for carrying on the work of Catechizing: that is in reſpect
<pb facs="tcp:119643:15"/>
               <hi>of the Form to be uſed,</hi> I doe not indeed uſe, nor have I put into the hands of my people <hi>the Catechiſms of the late reverend Aſſembly,</hi> not that I do diſown, or in any thing diſlike thoſe Forms, I ſully aſſent to the Characters by you gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of them, and by which you commend them; but the form I have choſen and put into the hands of my people, is that of reverend Mr. <hi>Ball,</hi> the goodneſſe, nay ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptableneſſe of which, among peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is proclaimed by the very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reiterated impreſsions of it; neither doth it differ in doctrine any thing, and in form not much from the Aſſemblies. The impulſive cauſe of my uſing this form was this, In the countrey where I lived this was the Catechiſm uſed in common, in the uſe of this I had by the bleſsing of God been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant:
<pb facs="tcp:119643:15"/>ſome that had learned this under my Miniſtry in the Countrey made mention of it amongſt the people with whom I then laboured, in ſo much that they generally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired this Catechiſm, and would admit no other: I condeſcending to their deſire in a three years uſe of it, not only did the fame of it come to the ears, but many Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſms into the hands of this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple before your exhortation came abroad; ſo that I could not conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently alter the form: herein I muſt beg, and cannot but hope, that none of my brethren will be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or cenſure me as guilty of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity, and the rather for that you cannot but all conclude by this Catechiſm,
<note place="margin">Exhort. to Catech.</note> 
               <hi>youth may be taught who made them, why he made them, how good and happy man was made by God, how evill and
<pb facs="tcp:119643:16"/>wretched he made himſelf, what need he had that the Lord Jeſus ſhould die for him, that the holy Ghoſt ſhould regenerate him: what priviledges he doth enjoy and may expect by Chriſt, what duties he is obliged to by thoſe priviledges, how he is to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent his petitions to God, how to receive the ſeals of Gods gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious covenant;</hi> which being gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, I muſt expect your promiſe <hi>not too moroſely to ſtand on circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial differences, where there is ſo fair an accord in material prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reverend Fathers and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> now that you have ſo ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and ſeaſonably called unto Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizing, I could heartily wiſh, that confirmation of children, which I cannot but look on as an engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:119643:16"/>to the ſtudy of the Catechiſm, were taken into your ſerious and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thoughts, and if found (as it hath been deemed) an Ordinance of God, ſome means were propounded for the reviving it in the Church: but herein I may ſeem too bold, and be thought to preſcribe matter to your conſiderate debates: I ſhall therefore forbear any further to trouble you: but aſſure you that God will counſell you in things which concern his Church: make men in place and power a bleſsing to his Church: give to brethren a ſpirit of union with and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcanſion to your juſt and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reſolves, and to our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of ready and cheerfull ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion to your exhortations and commands, and that not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you exhort and command du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but alſo with the authority of
<pb facs="tcp:119643:17"/>our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, is and ſhall be the hearty and conſtant prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Reverend Sirs, </salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The meaneſt of your brethren and ſervants in the work of the Goſpel,</hi>Zach. Crofton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119643:17"/>
            <head>CATECHIZING Gods Ordinance: OR, A ſhort Treatiſe concerning that ancient, approved and edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exerciſe of <hi>Catechizing.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HEB. 5.12. &amp; 6.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>When as for the time ye ought to be teachers, ye have need that we teach you what are the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Word of God.</p>
                  <p>Leaving therefore the Doctrine of the beginning of Chriſt, let us be led forward to perfection.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Author of this Epiſtle, (whether <hi>Paul,</hi> as is moſt probable, or any other, we ſhall not now diſpute) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſingularly ſtudious of the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119643:18"/>of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> in the Doctrine of Jeſus Chriſt they had received: in oppoſition to the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſeducing doctrine of ſuch as endevoured the drawing them back to the Leviticall prieſthood, and law of ceremonies; doth at large dictate, and make known, the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, certainty, and perſpicuity of the Lord his prieſthood: (the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of which, with the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall priviledges thereof, is the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of every Chriſtian ſoul well ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated, in the firſt and chief prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Religion) doth purſue their edification and eſtabliſhment herein, by two things amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to be ſpecially taken notice of in the text, as the parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>Firſt is a
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebrae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos pulſat placida re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſtuporis eorum.</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reus in Loc.</note> 
               <hi>Redargution</hi> or ſharp check for their unprofitableneſs under the Word, and Doctrine of Chriſt: of which they are convicted, by their haeſitation in the firſt principles of the Chriſtian doctrine, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, without any progreſſe, nay al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt any knowledge of them, as in chap. 5.12.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119643:18"/>
            <p>Secondly, a <hi>ſerious</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Objurgationi tarditatis ſubjicit exhortationem ad fidci profectum.</hi> Par. c. 6. ver. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Exercitation,</hi> or rather a ſolid declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his intention, to lead them (not of,
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jubet autem omitti e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſmodi rudimenta, non quod eorum obliviſci un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam debeant fideles, ſed quia in illis minime eſt haerendum.</hi> Calv. in Heb. c. 6. ver. 1.</note> but) from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the Doctrine of God, unto the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and fuller conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of higher mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that concerned Chriſt, their eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and perfection in him.</p>
            <p>Again in the redargution, we may (for the further: underſtanding of the words) obſerve, firſt a duty im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, as neceſſary and uſefull in the Church of God: and that is <hi>to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed and taught to know, what are the firſt rudiments of religion, ſo as to be able to teach others therein:</hi> for we muſt not learn and leave them <hi>(i. e.)</hi> forget them, no, but we muſt not ſtick faſt there and go no further: he is an idle and unskilful architect, that is alway buſie in laying a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and never rears up a building upon it:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pemble</hi> Preface.</note> where duty is not to be neglected, can be no ground of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, <hi>for the time ye ought to be teachers, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119643:19"/>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>Hebrews</hi> failing in and ſinful neglect of this duty, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting them to a neceſſity of being continued in and under the ſame: <hi>ye have need, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, from the exhortation or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the Author, we may take a ſerious view of his motion in the edification of the people of God; and we ſee,</p>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>terminum a quo,</hi> terme from which he moves, and it is expreſſed either</p>
            <p n="1">1. Generally, <hi>leaving the Doctrine of the beginning of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Or in the particular heads there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: as <hi>repentance from dead works, faith in Chriſt, the Doctrine of Baptiſme, of laying on of hands, reſurrection from the dead, and eternal Judgement:</hi> which according to the judgement of all Expoſitors on the Text, were the Catechetical heads of the Apoſtles Catechiſm, as we ſhall note here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>terminum ad quem,</hi> the terme to which, was to be <hi>led for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward towards perfection:</hi> where by the way we may obſerve the Apoſtles
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119643:19"/>method of teaching the Doctrine of Chriſt ſutable to every Infant capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that can only digeſt milk: as well as men of years, that did require ſtronger meat: nay that the word is to be diſpenſed, firſt in rudiments or Catechetical principles, as a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, on which muſt be built fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Doctrines.</p>
            <p>Having divided the words into their main and proper parts: before we come to conclude the doctrinal obſervation that ariſeth from them, it is expedient a little to explain them, and in the explication thereof, we ſhall finde there is not much difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that which principally as to our purpoſe cals for conſideration is what the Apoſtle means by the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>the elements of the beginning of the Word of God,</hi> which he expreſſeth in the 5. chap. 12. verſ. and cals in the 6. chap. 1. verſ. <hi>the Doctrine of the beginning of Chriſt:</hi> in the clearing of which to your judgements, we ſhall commend to your ſerious and ſecond thoughts three conſiderable things in the Text.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119643:20"/>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt is the Epithite, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Apoſtle doth denominate the ſame to us: for denominations de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate the quality of things.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond the Apoſtle his Method of teaching, touched on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third the Matter recited and expreſſed by the Apoſtle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>From all which we ſhall finde, that theſe elements are no other then the main and principal heads of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrine, Catechetically taught in the Church of God: and firſt of the firſt, and that is</p>
            <p>The Epithite or denomination; the Apoſtle cals them, <hi>elements of the beginning of the Word of God:</hi> Now <hi>elements</hi> are nothing elſe but the firſt principles and ſtanding verities of any Art or Science compendiouſly expreſſed, that being true in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they may be rules from which the fuller doctrine doth flow by clear and undeniable inference, and by which it may be proved for the initiating and edification of ſuch as are ſtudious of that Art or Science:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119643:20"/>ſuch are the ABC to children, the parts of ſpeech to the learning of Grammar, the Predicables and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicaments in Logick, and the like: this deſcription of Elements in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral we may finde ſuggeſted by the various Etymologies of the Latine word <hi>Elementum,</hi> which ſome ſo call <hi>quaſi alimentum, nouriſhment;</hi> becauſe others are begotten and brought forth by it; Some <hi>Elevamentum, an aiding or liſting up;</hi> becauſe other things take their beginning by their help, or that they are lifted up above, or before other principles, as more eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential and neceſſary: or <hi>Elicimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, deduction or drawing out,</hi> becauſe other things are extracted or drawn out of them.</p>
            <p>When we ſee them Elements in themſelves to be firſt verities and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider them related to the Doctrine of God, the reſult cannot but reſolve the Apoſtle to ſpeak of Catechetical doctrine, eſpecially when we adde to it the ſecond thing propounded, which is,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Apoſtle his Method in ſpeaking to them, which in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119643:21"/>of the Text we have before noted to be by way <hi>of check or blame</hi> for not being diligent in thoſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines which had been moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for their firſt ſetting forward in the profeſſion of Chriſt: which had been as milk for babes, ſutable for their weak capacities, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared them for the right and ready receiving of higher doctrines, that conduced to perfection: and then by proceeding from thoſe things which were to have been learned for the initiating them in the Doctrine of Chriſt, unto thoſe things that ſhould increaſe and build up their knowledge toward perfection, that ſo he might not alwaies reſt in the foundation, what can we imagine the Apoſtle to mean by foundation, and firſt doctrine from which he would thus in order go forward, but the Catechetical heads and ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding verities of the Goſpel?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if we obſerve the ſeveral heads recited and expreſſed by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor himſelf in chap. 6. verſ. 1, 2. as the things they ought to have lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but had neglected, (being ſuch as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119643:21"/>theſe before named, <hi>repentance from dead works, faith in Chriſt, Doctrine of Baptiſms, laying on of hands, reſurrection from the dead, and eternal Judgement)</hi> we cannot but determine them to be Catechetical heads taught to the novices and young Chriſtians for the grounding of them in the Doctrine of Chriſt, the which we finde alſo reſolved by the learned in their Expoſitions on the Text, as <hi>Deodate</hi> on the place ſaith, <hi>Theſe are the heads of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrine or Catechiſm, which were taught little children and novices in a plain, lowly and rough manner: Aretius</hi> thinks, <hi>that from hence may be gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed what were the principles and chief heads of the Catechiſm of thoſe times. Beza</hi> affirms they were the <hi>chief heads of Chriſtianiſm, which they call Catechiſm, and were delivered in ſhort and few words to the ignorant. Pareus</hi> cals them the firſt <hi>rudiments of Chriſtian faith,</hi> were wont to be learned by and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired from Children and young Chriſtians. But <hi>Calvin</hi> determines (from the teſtimony of the Fathers) that <hi>they were certain heads which the Paſtour uſed to aske the Catechized:</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119643:22"/>that the Author of the Epiſtle did look back to the form of Catechiſm then uſed in the Church: with whom <hi>Marlorat</hi> doth agree not only in judgement, but alſo in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, cannot but convince every one ſtudious of the minde of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, of the neceſſity and divine authority of Catechizing, whileſt we ſee the words thus divided and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, to lay before the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and in them all other Chriſtians thoſe two poſitive and undeniable du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt is to be well Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chized or inſtructed in the firſt and main grounds and principles of the Chriſtian Religion, that thereby as by a foundation layed, they may be made capable of higher Doctrines.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That being prepared by their Catechiſm, they muſt not haeſitate in (though not renounce or recede from) firſt elements, but diligently proceed to grow in the knowledge of the doctrines of a higher degree dictated to them: the firſt of theſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119643:22"/>is that I deſire may be taken into conſideration: and therefore from the particular duty dictated by the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> I ſhall reſolve for our inſtruction this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Obſervation or point of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Catechizing or inſtruction in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Religion is a Goſpel-exerciſe,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>and of neceſſity to be uſed in the Churches of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the proſecution of this truth, we ſhall endevour this Method, to which I ſhall deſire diligent atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By way of illuſtration, we ſhall conſider the word and thing Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techize.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Propound the reaſons that may confirm and clear the truth to your judgements.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Further illuſtrate the point by conſidering the matter and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of this exerciſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And laſtly make ſome uſe or application of the point.</p>
            <p>Firſt of the firſt of theſe, and that is, <hi>to conſider the word, and thereby the thing Gatechize.</hi> Concerning which I
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119643:23"/>muſt deſire you to obſerve that the word <hi>Catechize</hi> is no proper Engliſh word,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Viva voce inſtituo,</hi> or <hi>dicta repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</hi>
               </note> but derived of a Greek word which ſignifies <hi>to teach or inſtruct by a lively and audible voice,</hi> by the repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of words as by the reflexion of an eccho; and it is generally uſed for any kinde of inſtruction or information whatſoever, as in Act. 21.24.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>They are informed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thee.</hi> Gal. 6.6. <hi>Thoſe that are taught in the word, to him that teacheth.</hi> But more eſpecially and properly for inſtruction in the firſt rudimeuts of any doctrine: but moſt eſpecially and principally the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, ſee Rom. 2.18. <hi>Catechized in the Law:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, docere incepit, paulat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m aſſuefecit.</note> ſo in Act. 8.15. Luk. 1.4. this word <hi>Catechize</hi> in the Greek, anſwereth unto <hi>Hanach</hi> in the Hebrew which ſignifies to inſtruct, to begin to teach, to accuſtome by a little; alluding unto Dyers, that by degrees do dip and give colours to their Stuffs; hence comes the Hebrew word <hi>Hanich,</hi> which ſignifies a novice, or one in learning the firſt rudiments; both which are frequently read in the Old Teſtament. From the ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119643:23"/>of the word thus opened we may eaſily collect and conclude what is the thing, and we ſhall finde that</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Catechizing is a plain, perſpicuous and familiar way of teaching the ignorant and weak capacities in the firſt rudiments and principles of the Chriſtian Religion, drawn from the Doctrines of the Prophets and Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is that exerciſe whereby babes in Chriſt are fed with milk, and prepared for the receiving and digeſting of ſtronger meat: this is that that layeth the foundation of Chriſt in the ſoul, which muſt by higher Doctrine be built up unto perfection: and this then is the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God and Goſpel exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe to be uſed in the Churches of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Having briefly paſt the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the word and thing, we come now to ſpeak to the ſecond thing propounded, and therein to lay before you the reaſons that may prove Catechizing to be a Goſpel exerciſe, and to be uſed in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of God; the which we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve into theſe heads, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119643:24"/>cleared to our judgements cannot but convince of the truth of the point.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The excellency</hi> of Catechizing.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The antiquity</hi> of Catechizing.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>The neceſſity</hi> of Catechizing.</item>
                  <item>4. <hi>The utility or profit</hi> of Catechizing.</item>
                  <item>5. <hi>The facility or eaſines</hi> of Catechizing.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> The firſt reaſon is from the <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Catechizing;</hi> for that which appears to be a duty excellent, will plead divine ſtamp and call for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment in the Churches and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the people of God the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent upon earth, Pſal. 16.3.</p>
            <p>Now (my brethren) we ſhall on ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious obſervation finde Catechizing to be ſo far from a baſe, low, carnal and beggerly exerciſe, that it hath alwaies been in the Church of God, and been had in great eſteem and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence as very excellent, yea as ſuch an exerciſe which the greateſt Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, moſt honourable Senators, and chiefeſt of Martyrs for Gods truth thought ſutable to themſelves and worthy their ſubjection: nay to which alſo the wiſeſt Philoſophers and moſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119643:24"/>reverend Fathers of the Churches: ſuch as <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> as <hi>Auguſtine, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> and others, cheerfully ſubmitted to when God opened their eyes and inclined their hearts to the embracing and profeſſion of Chriſtian Religion: <hi>Juſtinus Martyr</hi> inſerts the uſe of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizing as an excellency to the Chriſtians in his perſwaſive Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies exhibited to the Emperour and Senate of <hi>Rome:</hi> it cauſed admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox</hi> Acts and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents.</note> French Doctors when but exerciſed by the children of <hi>Merindoll: Martin Luther</hi> thought it his glory to profeſſe himſelf <hi>diſcipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Catechiſmi</hi> a learner of the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme. But the excellency of this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will appear by laying before you,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The preſcribers</hi> of Catechizing.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The profeſſors</hi> of Catechizing.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>The proper matter</hi> of Catechizing.</item>
                  <item>4. <hi>The peculiar end</hi> of Catechizing.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt evidence of the excellency of Catechizing is from the <hi>preſcriber of it:</hi>
               <note n="1" place="margin">Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing.</note> the Author of every work ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth much to the luſtre and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the ſame: the excellency
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119643:25"/>then of this exerciſe is exceeding great, whiles it owns no other au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor then, <hi>excellency it ſelf,</hi> the wiſe all knowing, and all ſoveraign God, who taught it by his Spirit to his people in the daies of <hi>Adam,</hi> and of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and afterwards commanded it to his people the Jewes, in Exod. 12.26, 27. <hi>When your children aske. &amp;c. you ſhall ſay, It is the Lords paſſeover.</hi> Pſal. 78.5, 6. He <hi>commanded our fathers that they ſhould teach their children.</hi> From theſe places, as alſo from Deut. 4.9. <hi>Teach them thy ſons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">His dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for Chriſtian life. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 37.</note> Mr. <hi>Downam</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth Gods command for Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing. Moreover, in Deut. 6.7. we ſee God enjoyning this duty, whileſt he commands that they rehearſe or whet on the mindes of their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren his Lawes: ſo likewiſe Deut. 11.19. the word which is uſed to rehearſe, comes from an Hebrew root <hi>Schanan,</hi> to whet or ſharpen by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition of ſtrokes, Theſe commands (<hi>Ainſworth</hi> tels us) the Rabbies do underſtand of Catechizing; who him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alſo tels us God preſeribes here a brief Catechiſm in the grounds of Religion. Beſides we finde Wiſdome
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119643:25"/>expreſly to direct this exerciſe, in Prov. 22.6. <hi>Train up or inſtruct</hi> (it may be read <hi>Catechize) a childe in the daies of his youth:</hi> the Hebrew reads it, teach a childe at his mouth, that is, as nurſes feed Infants with the breſt or ſpoon at the mouth: ſo teach children by putting words in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their mouths, which can be no other way then by Catechizing: ſo we ſhall alſo finde it preſcribed in the New Teſtament, to paſſe by the Text which doth clearly declare it to be a duty: we ſhall finde Chriſt directing, nay commanding <hi>Peter,</hi> and in him all Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel <hi>to feed as well his lambs as his ſheep:</hi> which Mr. <hi>Downam</hi> notes to be an impoſing of this duty or exerciſe of Catechizing on Miniſters: and God by <hi>Paul</hi> directs fathers to bring up their children in the inſtruction and information of the Lord, Epheſ. 6.4. So that I may well conclude God himſelf to be the Author of Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, and it therein to be exceeding excellent.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note n="2" place="margin">Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> As Catechizing is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in reſpect of God the preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119643:26"/>thereof: ſo alſo in reſpect of <hi>the profeſſors and practitioners thereof,</hi> whom we ſhall finde to have been the Lords boſome friends and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deared people, the righteous who are the excellent on earth, ſuch as God hath highly prized and admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to familiarity with himſelf, as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Joſhua, David, Jehoiada,</hi> which in the ſecond reaſon (ſhall God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) be more fully manifeſted, and it is more then probable that Jeſus Chriſt did countenance and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend as exceeding excellent this exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe by his ſubmiſſion to it at twelve years of age, (although full of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and underſtanding, able to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with the Doctors) this Mr. <hi>Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam</hi> collects from Luk. 2.46. where it is ſaid Chriſt ſate among the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors; he conceives amongſt the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techumeni</hi> under the Doctors, which conjecture ſeems to be ſuggeſted by <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Marlorat</hi> on the place, who declare their judgements to be, that Chriſt ſate under, or before the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Law, not in their chair, for that the time of his preaching was not yet come.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119643:26"/>
            <p>Thirdly,
<note n="3" place="margin">Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> 
               <hi>the proper matter of Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing,</hi> proclaims the excellency there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: in that it is the Doctrine of God, the ſum of the Goſpel, the chief heads and principles of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, inferred and clearly flowing from the writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles: this is that excellent and celeſtial matter with which the minde being enlightned takes up the whole affections and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth on a man to the contempt of all excellencies under the ſun, yea even of life it ſelf for the enjoyment of it: this is the ſum of Wiſdome more precious then Rubies and moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Pearls, in the finding of which is life and the favour of the Lord. Now that this kinde of Doctrine is and ought to be properly and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally the matter of this exerciſe, as the Ordinance of God in his Church, I ſhall more fully clear to you in the third thing propounded to be ſpoken to <hi>(viz.)</hi> the matter and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Catechizing.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly,
<note n="4" place="margin">Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> the excellency of Catechizing appears by the <hi>pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar end thereof,</hi> which is no other
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119643:27"/>then the higheſt excellencies of Gods glory and the ſalvation of the ſoul, to which we may ſee this exerciſe to carry, by planting the knowledge and remembrance of God in youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, even infant mindes; by putting poſterity into a capacity of ſounding Gods praiſes for paſt favours; pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully bending the ſoul into the good and righteous way from which it will not depart in old age, by preſerving truth in its purity, and the ſoul from apoſtaſie, and placing in the heart principles directive to all duties in all conditions and eſtates whatſoever: this end is not only commended to us in the divine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of this exerciſe, and as it is the Centre of all Scripture inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: but we ſhall finde it expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared, that <hi>Timothy</hi> his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Scripture in and from his childhood (which with <hi>Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi> we may conclude more then probably he had learned by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction or Catechizing from his Mother and Grandmother) is able to make the man of God wiſe unto ſalvation, 2 Tim. 1.5.3.15. the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119643:27"/>of Catechizing appearing to be thus great, I hope will expell all baſe thoughts concerning it, and perſwade your ſpirits that it is a Goſpel exerciſe to be uſed in the Churches of God. We therefore paſſe from that to the conſideration of the ſecond reaſon of the doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> The ſecond reaſon is the <hi>antiquity of this excellent exerciſe.</hi> For that which is moſt ancient is alwaies granted to be moſt true: the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is moſt ancient, and this as a ſpecial part thereof, will be found of equall antiquity; and when we ſhal conſider it to have ſtood in the Church as long as the Church hath ſtood on the earth: to have been of old eſteemed, obſerved and practiſed in the Church of the Jewes and Chriſtians, it muſt needs be the more authentick, and lay the greater obligation upon us for the continuance of the ſame; and in enquiry after the age of it we muſt needs reſolve it elder then <hi>Methuſelah,</hi> whileſt we may trace the foot-ſteps of it from <hi>Adam</hi> to this preſent age: this duty was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the floud practiſed by <hi>Adam</hi> (as the learned do conclude) whoſe ſons
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119643:28"/>we finde offering ſacrifice to the Lord, in Gen. 4. unto which their father had inſtructed and brought them up, as well as to labour in the world, catechizing them in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Fall, and of the Seed of the woman, typified by their ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, whereby they were fitted for the right and reverent performance of the worſhip of God. Alſo it may be probably conjectured, that others of the Patriarchs did practiſe this duty; <hi>Henoch</hi> the ſeventh from <hi>Adam</hi> (of whom it is recorded, <hi>that he wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with God,</hi> Gen. 5.14.) received his name <hi>Henoch</hi> from an Hebrew root <hi>Hanach</hi> (before noted to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, to initiate or inſtruct in the principles of Religion) as one dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated unto God, or inſtructed from his youth: after the floud they had this exerciſe of Catechizing in the principles of Religion, which was after put in writing,
<note place="margin">Greenh.</note> as the learned conclude, and called the oracles of <hi>Sibylla,</hi> which were nothing elſe but things taught and delivered by word of mouth. It is moſt clear, that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> did uſe this exerciſe with
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119643:28"/>much fruit and good in his family, we read in Gen. 14.14. that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> brought out and armed three hundred and eighteen men brought up (the Hebrew word <hi>Hanichim</hi> will bear it) catechized or inſtructed in his houſe when he went to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcue of his brother <hi>Lot:</hi> Mr. <hi>Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> obſerveth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Greenhams</hi> Treat. of <hi>Cate.</hi> p. 312.</note> 
               <hi>Iſaac</hi> his going out to pray: and the ſervant his pious and faithfull proſecution of his Maſters oath, in Gen. 24. to be the effect of <hi>Abraham,</hi> his Catechizing: and Mr. <hi>Downam</hi> doth very well obſerve <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> care and diligence in Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, to be the ground of Gods revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his ſecrets, and making known his Judgements to him, in Gen. 18.19. <hi>I know him that he will command his ſons and his houſhold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Downam</hi>'s Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> 
               <hi>that they ſhall keep my waies.</hi> From this reaſon Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> obſerveth,
<note place="margin">Willet in Locum.</note> that it was the godly pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Fathers to Catechize or inſtruct their families in the Doctrine of the creation of the world, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of man, deſtruction of the old world, Gods providence, the Meſſiah to be revealed, and everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life to come: with whom <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeus</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:119643:29"/>doth concurre adding that before the Law,
<note place="margin">Paraeus in Locum.</note> there was no publick Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, but the Fathers were Prieſts, Paſtors and Teachers, and the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were the <hi>Catechumeni,</hi> learning the Doctrines above recited: neither may we think this duty to have been neglected by <hi>Iſaac, Jacob,</hi> or <hi>Job,</hi> and others of the Patriarchs: the Hebrew Rabbies tell us,
<note place="margin">See alſo <hi>Pemble</hi>'s Preface.</note> that <hi>Samuel</hi> was brought unto <hi>Eli,</hi> that he might fit before <hi>Eli</hi> the Prieſt, and be by him accuſtomed to, or taught in the Law, or the Precepts as the <hi>Catechumeni</hi> were wont to be taught. <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Bathſheba</hi> were very diligent in the Catechizing or inſtruction of <hi>Solomon</hi> their ſon, in the waies of wiſdome, as himſelf declares in Prov. 4.4. <hi>He taught me and ſaid unto me, Let thine heart hold faſt my words:</hi> from whence <hi>Lavater</hi> inſerreth the duty of,
<note place="margin">Lavater in Loc.</note> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth by the example, all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an parents betimes to inſtruct their children in the chief heads of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion: alſo <hi>Jehoiadah</hi> the Prieſt had well taught and inſtructed the young King <hi>Joaſh:</hi> whereby he was enabled to rule, and did rule
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119643:29"/>well all the daies of <hi>Jehoiadah;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may we think this duty was neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by <hi>Joſiah</hi> that good King, who in the time of his youth, ſet himſelf to ſerve the Lord with zeal and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity: and alſo after the captivity, if we beleeve the Hebrew Rabbies, from the time of <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> unto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> there were never under four hundred houſes of Catechizing in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> at which time alſo they made their Decree, that at thirteen years of age their children ſhould be put to Catechizing: to which pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſeems to allude, when he ſpeaks of the Jewes, as Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in the Law, Rom. 2.18. And as we find the footſteps of Catechizing in all the ages of the Jewiſh Church, ſo we ſhall find it ceaſed not in them, but was alſo practiſed in all the ages of the Chriſtian Churches ſince the time of Chriſt; for beſides what was before noted of Chriſt his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to it at twelve years of age, amongſt the Jewes he ſeems practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally to commend it to us by Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing his Diſciples concerning their perſwaſion of himſelf in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119643:30"/>to the ignorant conceits of the men of the world, in Mat. 16. chap. 13.16. verſ. <hi>Whom ſay men that I am? Whom ſay ye that I am?</hi> after Chriſts aſcenſion, this exerciſe was very perſpicuous:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Greenham</hi>'s Treat. of Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, p. 664.</note> Mr. <hi>Greenham</hi> brings in <hi>Aegiſippus</hi> report, that by reaſon of Catechizing, there was never a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the world, but received an alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in their Heatheniſh Religion within forty years after Chriſt: in the Apoſtles daies and primitive times of the Church of God, there were two ſorts Catechized, the one <hi>adulti,</hi> Infidels converted to the faith, ſuch was <hi>Theophilus,</hi> who is in Luk. 1.4. ſaid to have been <hi>Catechized:</hi> ſo alſo <hi>Apollos,</hi> Act. 18.25. the Eunuch and <hi>Cornelius</hi> his houſhold: ſuch was Raib <hi>Auguſtine, Ambroſe,</hi> and divers others; ſome of which were called to Martyrdome, when in their Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm: all which were inſtructed in the Catechetical heads of the text, and then baptized.</p>
            <p>A ſecond ſort were Children, ſuch as were born under the covenant of believing Parents who were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized and afterward Catechized and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119643:30"/>made able to profeſſe their faith when they were confirmed by the laying on of hands.</p>
            <p>We read of many that bare the office of Catechizing in the Church of God: ſome think <hi>Paul</hi> to have been employed in it by reaſon of that expreſſion, 1 Cor. 14.59. that <hi>I may Catechize others. Euſebius</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth <hi>Mark</hi> to have been Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> as alſo <hi>Clemens, Origen,</hi> and <hi>Heraclas,</hi> and others of the Fathers in other places, <hi>Gregorie Nyſſen, Cyrill, &amp;c.</hi> The Church had the Books of <hi>Auguſtine, De rudibus Catechizandis,</hi> and Books <hi>de Symbolo ad Catechumenos:</hi> alſo <hi>Athonaſius</hi> his Synopſis of ſacred Scaipture, with others of the like nature. In after ages this exerciſe was owned and enjoyned by the Canons of <hi>Neoce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaria, Iberis, Braccaria</hi> and others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Luther</hi>'s time; who alſo in his time among other things contended for Catechizing with a ſpirit of zeal, making it of abſolute neceſſity in the Church as Lord and Ruler; urging the continuance of it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermiſſion, condemning the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119643:31"/>neglect thereof after whom the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral reformed Churches enjoyned it, and exhibited the neceſſity of it in their ſeveral confeſſions, compoſing Catechiſms ſutable to the degrees of reformation enjoyned and obtained. This exerciſe of Catechizing appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to have been thus anciently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved as well in the Jewiſh as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churches, I hope will ſilence all thoughts of the novelty thereof, and lead us to the conſideration of the third reaſon, which is the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſo ancient a duty.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, Catechizing muſt be uſed in the Church of God, becauſe it is <hi>exceeding neceſſary:</hi> which neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity upon ſerious &amp; ſecond thoughts, will appear to be great unto all ſuch as deſire to be found good profici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents in the School of Chriſt, even as neceſſary as ABC to a childe firſt going to School; as the rudiments of any Arts or Science a man deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to know and profeſſe; as a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to building, without which it cannot ſtand; as milk for babes new born; and therefore it is in Scripture held out in ſuch termes,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119643:31"/>and ſimilitudes <hi>(viz.) Principles, Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Foundation, Milk, &amp;c.</hi> All which the Apoſtle uſeth in the Text, teaching us that this neglected, the ſoul cannot be <hi>eſtabliſhed in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt,</hi> but be alwaies unſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and as children ready to be toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to and fro with every winde of doctrine, cannot be <hi>prepared for, and made capable of higher learning,</hi> to read readily the Doctrine of the Lords Prieſthood, and their priviledges thereby, and thoſe things that ſhould tend to the perfecting of their faith, and compleating of their comforts; this was the great cauſe of our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors ſharp reproof of the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> in the Text; for when he came to communicate to, and teach them higher leſſons in the Schoole of Chriſt, they were not yet perfect in the firſt form of the principles of Religion: nay they cannot <hi>grow forward in the graces of Gods Spirit,</hi> but like children without milk be lank and lean, alwaies ready to exſpire that principle of life that is in them: nay, laſtly, they cannot unchatechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, <hi>act and move orderly and methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119643:32"/>in the practiſe of their Chriſtian duties,</hi> but be very incident to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and diſorder: for without all doubt, one great cauſe of all that confuſion that is in mens mindes, and actions in theſe daies, is the want of Catechizing; whereby they might be enabled to digeſt thoſe general no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that flie in their brains into certain ſolid heads, and principles, which might be ſtanding rules for their direction. It being then an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe ſo very neceſſary; I hope none can or will deny it to be a uſefull duty in the Church; eſpecially if we conſider the next Reaſon, which is the profit and comfort of this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, Then we ſhall finde Catechizing, as not to be needleſſe, ſo to be very <hi>profitable and comfortable to the Church of God in general, and the ſubjects of it in particular:</hi> for by ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous enquiry, and ſenſible obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we ſhall finde it no barren plant in the Lords garden; nor yet fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ordinance to be rejected; but that which rightly uſed, and skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, improved, doth produce to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119643:32"/>the comfort of all Gods children, theſe ſeveral advantages.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizing.</head>
               <item>1. The preſervation of the purity of Religion.</item>
               <item>2. The propagation of it to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity.</item>
               <item>3. Preparedneſſe to increaſes in the knowledge of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>4. Profit by the Word.</item>
               <item>5. Prevention of falling into error.</item>
               <item>6. Preſent capacity of communion at the Lords Table.</item>
               <item>7. Powerfull diſpoſition to du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Advantage. </seg>1</label> Firſt, then it <hi>preſerveth the good eſtate of the Church, in the maintenance of purity of Religion:</hi> for a Catechiſm rightly framed and grounded on the Scripture, is a brief abſtract and compendium of <hi>the Law and the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,</hi> whereby all corruptions of doctrine or practiſe is eaſily and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly diſcerned and detected: and by diligence in this exerciſe, truth is made like the Goldſmiths touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, ready to receive with appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation all golden doctrine thereunto conſonant: but to make men fear to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119643:33"/>tender, (or if any dare preſume) readily to reject all baſe metals of falſe doctrines, or practical innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that are thereunto diſſonant, and yet may be ſometimes impoſed on the Church; for this <hi>ſum of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> (as it may be called) or to uſe <hi>Luthers</hi> word, <hi>Bible of the people,</hi> or ſum of Chriſtian Religion, doth with more perſpicuity and celerity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the truth, and with more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility and ſpeed pull off the vizard of a <hi>Sic dixit Dominus,</hi> thus ſaith the Lord, from the face of all falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Seducers: then the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, comparing, and conſidering of the whole body of the Scripture, and reſolving the ſame into Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſtical principles: which muſt be the way to oppugn the untruths impoſed, even as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſms in caſes of Phyſick: <hi>Cokes</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes in caſes of Law; and the ſhort axiomes and ſtanding principles of Philoſophy doe more quickly and ſharply detect all contrary aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, then the more large and ample Treatiſes and diſcuſſions of the ſame. Hence it may be more then probable,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119643:33"/>that the reaſon why the Lord Jeſus did no more particularly (by quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting books, chapters and verſes) prove the truth and purity of his Doctrine preached to the Jewes, was for that as the Apoſtle ſaith in Rom. 2.18. they <hi>knew his will and tryed thoſe things that did diſſent from it, being</hi> (as was noted before) <hi>catechized in the Law:</hi> we may afſo obſerve that <hi>Paul</hi> gave <hi>Timothy</hi> a Catechiſtical ſum of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrine, which in 2 Tim. 1.13. he cals a
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in Rom. 6.12. it is called, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Analogie of Faith.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>form of ſound words:</hi> and chargeth him to keep faſt the ſame, as a preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative of the purity of Religion, againſt the corruptions which our nature is too prone to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: hence alſo it was that the fathers of the primitive times did uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally reſolve certain Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſtical
<note n="*" place="margin">As the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, <hi>Epheſine,</hi> and of the ſeveral Councels againſt the Haereſies of <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Macedonius,</hi> and <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxius, Neſtorius,</hi> and <hi>Eutyches.</hi>
               </note> verities, into ſhort and ſtanding prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples for the defending of the Church in the pure truth of Chriſt Godhead, &amp; the like againſt the <hi>Arrian</hi> &amp; other Hereſies: and moreover
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119643:34"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:119643:34"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:119643:35"/>we may obſerve the Devils ſtrongeſt engine, againſt the purity and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of Religion to have been the obſtruction of this exerciſe; when he ſtirred up <hi>Julian</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, as his curſed inſtrument to make a more furious attempt, and prevailing aſſault then the ten firſt perſecutions on the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; by taking away Chriſtian books, and putting down all Schools of Cateehizing: for the Devil and his inſtruments were, and are ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that Catechizing is the thing that impedes the riſing of his kingdome; for that by it the foundation of Chriſtian Doctrine doth not only remain firm, but alſo the meaneſt members of the Church are made in ſome meaſure capable of contending for the truth, and communicating the ſame to ſuch as by the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of other parts and abilities are likely to enter the liſts with truths oppoſers in its defence, though many eminent pillars, even faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel be by their rage cut off: ſo that Martyrdome can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not maſter it, but rather propagate it;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119643:35"/>For <hi>ſanguis Martyrum</hi> becomes <hi>ſemen Eccleſiae</hi> by watering theſe Cateche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical heads of Goſpell Doctrine; and therefore the Spaniſh Jeſuites were wont to ſay they had moſt hopes when there was leaſt Catechizing; nay the Pope himſelf with all his curſed crew, do acknowledge the ground we have gotten of them hath been by Catechizing: the Pope complains, that the greateſt <hi>hurt that the ſons of the Heretiques had ever done him, was by their pestilential writings adorned with the title of Catechiſms:</hi> and the ground which they have gotten again of the Churches of God, hath bren by their more ſtrict exacting of their Catechiſms and our neglect of ſo profitable a duty.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Adv. </seg>2</label> 2. The ſecond Advantage is the <hi>propagation of Religion to poſterity:</hi> which lies on every Chriſtian as his poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive duty to advance and endevour, and therefore God commands the knowledge of his Works and Word to be made known <hi>to ſons, and ſons ſons, children, and childrens children,</hi> Deut. 4.9. It was this ſtanding Law of tranſmitting Religion to poſterity
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119643:36"/>by Catechizing Children, that indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Pſalmiſt to propound, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and provoke attention to the Catecheticall Doctrine of the Jewes, in Pſal. 78. And one great reaſon why God would make known his ſecrets unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> was that care God found in him by Catechizing to convey the knowledge of him, his works and judgements to poſterity. By this means ſucceeding generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are enabled to <hi>accompliſh the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking of progenitors in the ſolemn com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorations of the ſpecial mercies of God:</hi> Hereby the Jewes, as the Rabbies tell us, retain a reverent eſteem of their deliverance out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> with all its concomitants and effects; nay by this the truth of Chriſtian Religion hath been continued above ſixteen hundred years, and notwithſtanding the rage and fury of perſecutors en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devouring the utter eradication and extinction of it, hath by Catechiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſeed been derived unto, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived by ſucceeding generations.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Adv. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, it <hi>prepares to ripeneſſe in knowledge,</hi> being as the firſt draught of a picture, the baſe and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plot
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119643:36"/>on which the building is ſet; the firſt rules of any art or ſcience, which well learned makes ready for perfection in the Art and Science, and therefore it is called, <hi>the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Doctrine of Chriſt:</hi> and it is to be obſerved on experience, that they that have attained to the moſt perfect meaſure of knowledge of the Doctrine of Chriſt, were by Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing well entred into the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Adv. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, it makes us <hi>profit by the Word,</hi> when read by, or preached to us, whileſt by Catechizing men are enabled to refer what they read to their proper heads of Divinity, and reſolve them into ſummary conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which are very much infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the judgement, and convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to the conſcience, and clearly to diſcern truth from error, and diſtinguiſh between truth and truth, and ſee their dependance one on another differ the Law from the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel with their different ends of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation and comfort: whereby their underſtanding acting clearly and orderly will help the memory
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119643:37"/>to retain, quicken the affection, and make their growth ſenſible &amp; diſcerni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which being clouded by a confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed knowledge, makes many times profiting Chriſtians to complain of barrenneſſe under the Word. The care of the Apoſtles, to feed firſt with milk of principles ſuch as they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devoured to make and approve pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable under the meat of higher Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial Doctrines, doth clearly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to us this benefit of Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing: beſides, the cauſe of the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes</hi> incapacity of receiving and profiting by higher Doctrines, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly declared to be the little pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency they had made in the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion: and experimental obſervation doth witneſſe, that prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching doth little good where Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing is wanting; for we may well ſay with <hi>Bullinger,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bulling. Decad.</hi> 5. <hi>Ser.</hi> 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 907.</note> How ſhall the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple profit, when they underſtand not their Paſtour when he preacheth Law, Covenant, or Grace, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Adv. </seg>5</label> Fifthly, It <hi>prevents their falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fundamental errors,</hi> and following pernicious doctrine; whileſt by this means truth is founded and firmly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119643:37"/>fixed in their mindes and memories as a rule ready at hand to try all that is preached in the Name of the Lord; as a touchſtone, reſerved to detect all ſuch falſities as are gilded over with the name of Truth, when di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary thereunto; as a root whoſe ſeveral branches being ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſetled in the ſoul, makes them bear up the head, and ſtand to their Chriſtian ſtation, againſt the ſtormy tempeſt of all ſeducing doctrine: nay theſe are ſeeds of ſuch ſolid comforts, and earneſts of ſuch eternall joyes, as bears up the heart cheerfully to embrace, and readily to ſubmit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the moſt exquiſite and cruel tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments hell or earth can execute up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, rather then to deny the Faith, recede from the Truth, and make ſhipwrack of a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: ſouls ſoundly Catechized, are noble <hi>Bereans,</hi> receiving and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving the Word, becauſe confirmed by, and conſonant to Scripture; not becauſe ſpoken by Apoſtles: their judgements are ſwayed to the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of principles by ſound reaſon, not by by a ſeeming ſanctified life of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119643:38"/>the author or publiſher, knowing that <hi>falſe Apoſtles are deceitful workers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.13, 14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>and transform themſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt: and no marvel, for Satan is transformed into an Angel of light: it is no great thing then, if his Miniſters transform themſelves as though they were the Miniſters of righteouſneſſe, whoſe end will be according to their works:</hi> ſuch are <hi>Merindolian Martyrs,</hi> able to exhibit ſuch Scriptural confeſſionsof faith, as ſhall convince and confound ſuch doctors as are appointed to convince them of Hereſie, or (more proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) to ſeduce them from the truth of Chriſt, (which they called Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie) ſo as to confeſſe, that an eight daies ſtudy of ſuch a confeſſion, doth teach more Scripture then all the daies of their lives
<note n="*" place="margin">As did the Doctor ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Biſhop of <hi>Caveillon</hi> to detect the Hereſies in the confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by them exhibited.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; whoſe children are hereby enabled to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found learned Prelates, and aſtoniſh reverend Doctors; making Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſticall teaching, to
<note n="*" place="margin">As the religious man of <hi>Paris</hi> did profeſſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Children of <hi>Merindoll</hi> Catechize one another. <hi>Fox</hi> his Acts and Monuments, p 866.</note> tranſcend the divine Diſputations in the Schools of <hi>Sorborne</hi> in <hi>Paris:</hi> (nay
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119643:38"/>in a word) by this means they are ſo confirmed and eſtabliſhed in the faith, that they will ſooner ſubmit themſelves, their wives and children, I and their whole town to the cruel rage of outragious enemies, then ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelves to be moved away from the truth received and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by them. This exerciſe of Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing hath been ſo effectuall, to the eſtabliſhing of ſouls in the truth, that many by it have been prepared to Martyrdome, and enabled with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable patience to endure bitter ſcourging, and cruel torments,
<note place="margin">Seven of <hi>Origens</hi> Scholars at one time.</note> and burnings (even in their young and tender years) in defence of the truth: it is to the everlaſting honour of ſome of the Martyrs, Chronicled in Eccleſiaſtical ſtory, that they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the crown of Martyrdome, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yet but Catechumeniſts, whereas the reaſon of others falling away from the faith in the time of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, is noted to be, that they were not yet fully inſtructed in the Doctrine of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Adv. </seg>6</label> Sixthly, It <hi>puts into a preſent capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of communion at the Lords Table:</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:119643:39"/>it prepareth the heart unto the right and worthy receiving of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by delivers the ſoul from the great danger of <hi>eating and drinking judgement to himſelf:</hi> whileſt that by Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, they are fully informed and convinced of that faith and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine openly profeſſed, and ſealed by the Lords Supper, and therefore neceſſary to be known, before the participation of this ordinance, whileſt hereby they are inveſted with that neceſſary qualification of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, concerning mans miſery by ſin, recovery by Chriſt; Gods Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with man eſtabliſhed in the hands of a Mediator, the author, end, and inſtitution of this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; all which being Catetheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call heads muſt needs encourage the deſirous communicants, readily to ſubmit themſelves to the trial of the Church, with their deſire of admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Lords Table, with an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured confidence that their commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion cannot be denied on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ignorance, whileſt hereby
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119643:39"/>they are enabled to the diſcharge of that neceſſary duty of ſelf-examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion required by the Apoſtle in the Name of the Lord:
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.28.</note> in that by Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizing they come to know all thoſe neceſſary qualifications requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to render the ſoul ſutable for communion with God at this Table, whileſt they are made capable of diſcerning the Lords Body; in a Chriſtian way to diſtinguiſh the outward ſign from the inward grace and thing ſignified; whileſt hereby (being delivered from Popiſh dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) they are well taught that out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward elements are ſet before their outward ſenſes to reſemble and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent to the inward man the body and bloud of Jeſus Chriſt: nay in a word, whileſt hereby they have in readineſſe matter of contemplation (ſutable to ſuch an Ordinance) to the affectation of their hearts and excitation of their affections in their enjoyment, hereby they are in a good capacity of renewing their covenant with Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, of receiving the ſealing efficacy of that Ordinance to the ſoul,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119643:40"/>and with the <hi>Jewes</hi> to render an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt to any that ſhall demand of them the ground and end of their ſo frequent celebration of their Chriſtian Paſſeover; whereas through the want of this exerciſe, men are in danger of ruſhing unworthily and unprepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly to the receiving of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to preſſe unreverently to take thoſe things they do not know or underſtand the ground, end, or mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of; to taſte thoſe dainties that belong not to them, and take in hand thoſe duties they know not how to manage: in this regard the primitive times alwaies by their Cry of <hi>holy things for holy men</hi> ſent away among the common hearers and penitentiaries the <hi>Catechumeni,</hi> or ſuch as were learning their Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm, as men not yet ſutable for this Sacrament. Hence alſo it is, that the Canons and conſtitutions of the Church of God in all ages, even in the moſt corrupt times require that every one be Catechized before they receive the Sacrament: and this is the cauſe why the Diſcipline of the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119643:40"/>Church in this age and time requires an accompt of the knowledge of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one deſirous of the Lords Supper, that if any be found ignorant by reaſon of the paſt neglect of this duty they may by diligent Catechizing be made fit for it, and ſo be admitted to it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Adv. </seg>7</label> Seventhly, It <hi>puts on a man a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diſpoſition of diſcharging his duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and man:</hi> in that by Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizing they are not only taught to know the ſeveral Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the firſt and ſecond Table, but alſo are well inſtructed to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh duties appertaining to God from ſuch as belong to man, and to diſcern the ſeveral ſins forbidden, and duties therein commanded: <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s prayer and meditation, his ſubmiſſion in all things to his father; and the ſervants prayer to the God of his Maſter <hi>Abraham,</hi> and faithfulneſſe concerning his Maſter's Oath, was before noted to be the fruit of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizing: and it is to be obſerved on experience, that ſuch are moſt apt to rebellion and diſobedience towards
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119643:41"/>men, who are not Catechized in the Doctrine of God; and therefore <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> when he would ſelect to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſuch of his Court Officers as he would confide in to be truſty Counſellors and defenders of his perſon and Kingdome, tryed which of them were beſt inſtructed in the faith and fear of God, declaring ſuch only were worthy to be about a Prince as ſervants, that being true to their God would be loyall to him.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>5</label> The fifth and laſt reaſon why Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizing ſhould be uſed in the Church of God, is the <hi>eaſineſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of:</hi> which is very much, and ſo found upon experience, for it ſuiteth the Doctrine of Chriſt to the weakeſt capacity that is, and puts words in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the mouth; ſo as that by dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in this exerciſe, the ſoul that is moſt ignorant, knowing nothing of God, may be able in a ſhort time to give an account of his faith to any that ſhall aske it: becauſe of the facility of it. <hi>Children</hi> are in Scripture declared to be the ſubjects
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119643:41"/>thereof, and it is called <hi>rudiments,</hi> in which children, not men of years, are wont to be inſtructed; <hi>milk,</hi> with which babes and not men of ſtrength are to be nouriſhed: and although at the firſt it may ſeem (as all other ordinances of God) ſomething diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, yet a willing and diligent minde will prove it very eaſie; for it being a piece of the Lords yoke, which is all of it eaſie to be borne, cannot but be pleaſant to the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſpirit, although the fleſh may be found weak in ſubmiſſion to it.</p>
            <p>Having thus briefly paſt the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the point, which I hope up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſerious thoughts may clearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince any of the divine ſtamp of this exerciſe, and ſo juſtifie the uſe of it in the Churches of God, we come in the next place by way of illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the truth, to conſider what muſt be the <hi>matter and manner</hi> of this exerciſe of <hi>Catechizing.</hi> And,</p>
            <p>Firſt then of the ſubject Matter to be taught by Catechizing, which muſt not be as the Papiſt (wickedly
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119643:42"/>corrupting this exerciſe and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God) do make to teach matters altogether unprofitable, nay vain, falſe and frivolous, as the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of Fathers, the Canons of the Councel and conſtitutions of the Church inconſiſtent with the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Scripture: nay in many things directly contrary thereunto: neither yet muſt it be nice and curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous points, though true yet fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and unprofitable, tending more to tickle the brain, and affect the ſenſe, then to take with the heart and inform the judgement: but the matter of Catechizing muſt be <hi>all and only the chief heads and ſtanding veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Chriſtian Religion,</hi> ſummarily extracted out of the Scripture, and ſolidly grounded upon the ſame, that they may be propounded as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible rules for the triall of the aſſertions, as ſtanding principles, whence may naturally flow all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions conducing to the profeſſion of Chriſt with ſtedfaſtneſſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and as a ſure foundation upon which the fabrick of grace and of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119643:42"/>the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt may be erected and built up without all doubt of falling, nay with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of ſtanding againſt the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous aſſaults of all falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and fiery perſecution: and therefore the Church of God hath in different ages propounded thoſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall and ſpeciall verities, that in ſuch ages have been oppugned by gainſayers of the truth and the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Church, as Catechetical Doctrine to eſtabliſh the people of God in the Truths reſiſted. Thus did the <hi>Nicene</hi> Councell in the time of the <hi>Arrians</hi> Hereſie, and therefore the learned conſidering what ſhould be the heads of the Catechiſm, ſome have reſolved in generall the Law and the Goſpel: others the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, or Ten Commandements and Creed (commonly called <hi>Symbolum Apoſtolicum,</hi> Apoſtles Creed) others the Doctrine of Gods Will and his Works: others the Ten Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, the Creed, the Doctrine of Baptiſm, and the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and Prayer: others the miſery
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119643:43"/>of man by Sin, his recovery by Chriſt, and thankfulneſſe to God for ſo great mercy: but not to ſtand on the determination of the ſeveral particular heads, we may confound their ſeveral judgements, and finde them all center in the general before expreſſed, in which we may ſafely acquieſce, that the heads and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſtian Religion muſt be the matter of Catechizing, which may more fully be proved by theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> 1. It is <hi>preſcribed by God to his Church,</hi> in that by his Spirit he taught <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> to inſtruct his ſons in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the Meſſiah as the ground of Sacrifice: and to <hi>Abraham,</hi> the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of whoſe Catechiſm may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably conjectured to be the <hi>Covenant God made with him and with his ſeed:</hi> he expreſly commands <hi>the Doctrine of the Law and Paſſeover,</hi> to be the matter of the Catechiſms taught by the Jewes to their children, when in Exod. 12.26. When they celebrated the Paſſeover, God enjoyns them to ſhew their children, how God paſſed over them
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119643:43"/>in the land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the <hi>Doctrine of the Law,</hi> and Gods dealing with the <hi>Iſraelites, Moſes</hi> in the Name of the Lord preſcribes as the matter of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm, in Deut. 6.7. and from this Catechetical matter it is, that <hi>Paul</hi> cals them Catechized in the Law, in Rom. 2.18.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> The ſecond Reaſon, it was <hi>propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Chriſt and his Apoſtles;</hi> for we ſhall finde the ſum or matter of their Catechizing, to be the main princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſtian Religion; as in Chriſt his inſtruction of his Diſciples was in that main ſtanding princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Religion (ſo much oppugned by the world) that he was the Chriſt the Son of the living God: and the author of this Epiſtle gives us a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry clear account of the main heads of the Apoſtolick Catechiſm in theſe five heads, <hi>Faith in Chriſt, repentance from dead works, doctrine of Baptiſms, laying on of hands, and the Reſurrection of the dead,</hi> Heb. 6.2. Which are clear Scriptural and fundamental notions: and <hi>Timothy</hi> being Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chized, is ſaid to have learned the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119643:44"/>Scripture from his youth, 2 Tim. 3.15.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> The third Reaſon, <hi>This was the matter of Catechizing in the primitive and pure times of the Church after the Apoſtles;</hi> for they inſtructed in the Doctrine of the Trinity and faith in Chriſt the Mediator and the like, as may appear by ancient writings, and the Caterhiſms of the Fathers, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and others: We read of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny converted to the Faith of Chriſt in the Catechizing School of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> and ſo well grounded in the Faith of Chriſt, that they were fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for Martyrdome, and chearfully ſubmitted to the ſame. Six of <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens</hi> Diſciples, whereof ſome were but learning their Catechiſm, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded at one time to be led to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome: certainly then the matter of this exerciſe could be no other then the chief principles of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>The fourth Reaſon, It is only Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizing in Scripture Doctrine and principles of Religion, that <hi>train up in the fear of God in truth and godlineſſe,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119643:44"/>which all children ought to be educated in:</hi> this matter is proper to that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent end of this exerciſe <hi>(viz.)</hi> the glory of God and ſalvation of the ſoul, before ſpoken of; and therefore this only muſt be the matter of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizing; for in all effects to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, there muſt be a ſutableneſſe between the <hi>cauſa</hi> and the <hi>cauſatum.</hi> Theſe precedent reaſons being ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſidered, I hope may clear it to every rational man's judgement, that the matter of Catechizing muſt alwaies be the heads, and yet only the heads of Chriſtian Religion that are matters of Faith and ſtanding principles. And now before I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to make known to you the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of this exerciſe, I muſt make a little ſtay to remove an Objection framed from this matter againſt this exerciſe, thus:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Sir, ſeeing that the <hi>ſum of Chriſtian Religion extracted out of Scripture,</hi> as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, Faith, Sacraments, Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and the Doctrine of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and the like, muſt be as you ſay the proper matter of Catechizing,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119643:45"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:119643:45"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:119643:46"/>
               <hi>Wherein doth it differ from preaching?</hi> which we all know to be an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Jeſus Chriſt treating of the Doctrine of the Scripture, and that very matter that you have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to be the matter of this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe; and if it do not differ, may it not be ſufficient that we ſubmit to Preaching, but we muſt needs have Catechizing, which doth but the ſame thing impoſed on us, as ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary a duty, and diſtinct from Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> It will not follow: firſt, becauſe Preaching and Catechizing are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant about the ſame matter, nay and alſo carry on to the ſame end, that they are not different and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct duties each from other, for they may treat of the ſame matter in different manners; for though Faith and Hope are converſant about the ſame matter, the promiſes, and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the ſame end of accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and enjoyment, yet I hope no man will deny them to be different and diſtinct graces in the ſoul: and again, though the preaching of the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119643:46"/>Word, and adminiſtration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament commend to us the ſame mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Chriſt crucified, in ſo much as that they are called the one <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum audibile,</hi> the audible word to be heard; and the other <hi>verbum viſibile,</hi> the word to be ſeen, and ſo both the Word; yet it will not follow, but that they are different and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Ordinances, and not the ſame, even as the learning of ABC is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent and diſtinct from ready rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, which is but a recitall of the ſame material letters: and the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the firſt rules of any Art or Science is different from more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect proceeding in the ſame Art or Science, whether Logick, Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, or the like.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> Secondly, We ſhall now ſhew un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that though Catechizing and Preaching do treat of the ſame mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Doctrine of Scripture, yet they are different and diſtinct Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances in the Church of God, and not to ſtand on the conſideration of them as diſtinctly commanded in the Scripture, and have alwaies been
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119643:47"/>diſtinctly ſubjected to in the Churches of God, I ſhall ſatisfie my ſelf in ſhewing you wherein they differ, which I hope may ſatisfie you that they may not be confounded; the which Mr. <hi>Greenham</hi> that reverend and godly Author hath in part done before me, who notes them to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in theſe three things, unto which I ſhall adde two other.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Preaching is the dilating of one member of the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion into a whole Treatiſe: Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing is the contracting of the whole into a ſum.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Preaching is unto all ſorts, but Catechizing only to the younger, and rude, or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Preaching is not exacted to be repeated, Catechizing is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Catechizing principally informes the Judgement in the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Chriſtian Religion: but Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching doth chiefly excite the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and directs the heart in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the ſame.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:119643:47"/>
            <p>Fifthly, Catechizing layeth the foundation of Chriſt in the ſoul, and preaching builds upon it; that teacheth the ABC, or firſt rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, this perfecteth the knowledge of Chriſtian Doctrine. Having thus ſpoken of the matter, we come in the next place to ſpeak unto you of the manner of Catechizing, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which we ſhall propound three things to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Some rules concerning the formes of Catechiſm to be uſed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Who muſt Catechize, and how they muſt demean themſelves in this duty.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Who muſt be Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and how they muſt carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in it.</p>
            <p>Firſt of the firſt of theſe, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the formes of Catechizing to be uſed, obſerve theſe four rules.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The matter, heads and grounds of Catechizing, are contained and expreſſed in Scripture, and therefore alwaies the ſame; but the formes are not, but left to the liberty of the Church, and therefore variable ſo,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119643:48"/>as that we are not ſo preciſely ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the form as we are to the matter.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such formes are moſt fitting, as may be found to tend moſt to the edification of the Church, in confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming them in the truths and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples moſt oppoſed, in which reſpect the Church hath taken liberty to vary.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is very expedient and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, that there be in the Church two formes of Catechiſm, a ſhorter and more eaſie for the younger ſort which are not yet able to learn and commit to memory a larger; and a larger wherein for the riper ſort the principles of Religion are more fully handled.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Every form uſed muſt be found brief, plain, orderly, and by way of queſtion and anſwer eaſie; for that this form of teaching is moſt expedient, as by way of queſtion and anſwer.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is moſt ſutable to the rude and ignorant infant capacity by putting words into their mouthes,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119643:48"/>helping them to anſwer and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand when they ſee the queſtion propounded and anſwer to be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As enjoyned to the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who are required to whet upon their children their Catechetical Doctrine, which can no otherwaies be done, then by repetition of the ſtrokes of the ſame ſubject.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, As practiſed by Jeſus Chriſt when willing to receive an account of his Diſciples profiting under his Miniſtry, and to confirm them in the Faith in oppoſition to the common fame of the world, Whom ſay ye that I am?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, As that which puts them into an aptitude and readineſs of rendring an account of the faith that is in them to every one that asketh, being hereby better enabled to retain and reſolve anſwers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to queſtions ſuddenly propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (but before known) then the knowledge of bare notions without the queſtions to which they anſwer.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:119643:49"/>
            <p>The ſecond thing conſiderable in the manner of Catechizing, is the perſons that muſt Catechize, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their carriage in this duty; now the perſons that muſt do it, will be found to be three ſorts of men:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Miniſters in their Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Schoolmaſters in their Schools.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Maſters of families in their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſort that muſt Catechize muſt be <hi>Miniſters,</hi> that have taken up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them the Paſtoral charge of a congregation to feed them with knowledge and underſtanding accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſeveral capacities of the ſouls, as well young as old under their charge: and that it is their duty, may appear by theſe enſuing reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>The careful performance of this duty by the faithful Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and moſt eminent and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Fathers of the primitive times: not to ſtand upon the probability of <hi>Paul</hi>'s Catechizing, from 1 Cor.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119643:49"/>14.19. it is much more than pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that it was done in the Church of the Hebrewes by the Author of this Epiſtle, who ſharply checks their non-proficiency in this duty. <hi>Euſebius</hi> tels us, that before <hi>Pantenus, Clemens, Origen, Mark</hi> the Evangeliſt did Catechize at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> which was commended in him by <hi>Philo Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deus,</hi> which three were themſelves Catechizers in the ſame Church of <hi>Alexandria</hi> in the years of our Lord Two hundred, and two hundred and fifty, each ſucceeding other, <hi>Origen</hi> being ſet up by the diligent over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of <hi>Demetrius</hi> their Biſhop; and after whom ſucceeded <hi>Heraclus,</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius Alexandrinus,</hi> and others: alſo about the ſame time we read of <hi>Optatus,</hi> Catechizer at <hi>Carthage</hi> in the daies of <hi>Cyprian:</hi> alſo the ſeverall Catechiſms of the Fathers, as <hi>Cyrill, Gregory, Nicen,</hi> the books of <hi>Auguſtine de Catechizandis rudibus;</hi> and his four books <hi>ad Catechumenos; Athanaſius</hi> his Synopſis of ſacred Scripture; and <hi>Fulgentius de fide ad diaconum,</hi> do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim that conſcionable care they had
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119643:50"/>to the diſcharge of this duty: and the duty of Miniſters for the edifying of the body of Chriſt being alwaies one and the ſame, their conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſcharge of this exerciſe doth declare it to be a Miniſterial duty.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>A Miniſter by preaching doth not diſcharge his duty, if he neglect Catechizing:</hi> becauſe thereby he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs only thoſe that are <hi>adulti,</hi> men of years, and ſtrength to digeſt ſuch meats, and either wholly neglects to feed youth, no leſſe committed to his charge as members of the Church, or elſe adminiſters that food which is unſutable and cannot be by them digeſted, in ſtead of the milk of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Religion, of which even babes in Chriſt and almoſt in years are capable: and truly we have cauſe to ſuſpect one great cauſe of young mens high flown oppoſition of the truth and Ordinances of God, to ſpring from their affected hearing of thoſe things in preaching which they cannot digeſt into orderly nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment, becauſe they have not by the milk of Catechizing been prepared thereunto.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:119643:50"/>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Miniſters ought to Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chize to make all his pains and preaching the more profitable to his hearers,</hi> by keeping freſh in their mindes and memories thoſe ſtanding notions of Chriſtian Religion, which he doth by preaching more particularly il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate, more fully prove, and more powerfully apply to their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That thereby he may more clearly diſcern the eſtate of his flock, obſerve the Maſters of fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies in their proper places to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their duties, and ſee their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency in grace and knowledge un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all the Ordinances of God by him diſpenſed, confirming them in the truth learned, which is clear to have been the reaſon of Chriſt his Catechizing of his Diſciples after his long preaching, and many miracles amongſt them, in Mat. 13.51. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving preached to them many para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, he asketh them if they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand: and Mat. 16.13, 14. Whom ſay men, whom ſay ye that I am?</p>
            <p>Fifth and laſt reaſon why Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119643:51"/>muſt Catechize in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, is that they may <hi>detect all lurking deceivers that lie in wait to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the people committed to their charge from the truth, and diſcern when any of them begin to be tainted with error and falſe doctrine,</hi> whereby they are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected how to improve themſelves as skilful workmen in the Lords houſe, dividing the Word aright, defending the truth and ſoul with which he is charged, ſtopping the mouth of all gainſayers: which is the great reaſon of that general Apoſtolical charge of holding faſt the form of ſound words, in 2 Tim. 1.13. and commendation of obeying the form of Doctrine in Rom. 6.17. which the learned conclude to be Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm.</p>
            <p>Having thus given you the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why Catechizing is the duty of Miniſters, I ſhall paſſe from this with this hearty deſire, that God would put into the hearts of all his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to perform their duty herein in theſe backſliding daies, wherein the principles of Religion are ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:119643:51"/>unknown and declined: and ſo I come to conſider the ſecond ſort of Catechiſts, which are School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters in their Schools, whoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in the diſcharge hereof ſhould write really what is worthily writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten on the wals of that famous School of this City at <hi>Paules, Schola Catechiſationis puerorum in optima &amp; maxima fide Chriſti;</hi> and for theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the main and chief end of erecting Schools, was alwaies <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in, and preparation to divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip:</hi> for even among the Pagans they did appoint Schools to the end that the Oracles of their gods might be read to the youth, and they Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophically prepared to purſue the <hi>ſummum bonum</hi> of the ſoul: and among the Papiſts to inſtruct and train up in traditions of the Fathers and C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the Church concerning the corrupt worſhip of God; whom it were an exceeding ſin and ſhame for Chriſtian Schoolemaſters in the reformed Churches to come ſhort of by not inſtructing in
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119643:52"/>the true worſhip of the true God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As this was the end of Schools in general, ſo we ſhall ſee that in Church of God, <hi>among the Jewes and alſo among the Chriſtians, Schools were conſtituted and conſerved by the ſpecial providence of God, for the inſtruction of youth in ſhe Doctrine of his worſhip, as well as other learning.</hi> The eight and forty cities of the Levites were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed abroad through all the tribes of the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that they might be as Schools wherein the youth might drink in the Doctrine of the Law and the Prophets, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the knowledge of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral Arts: ſuch as theſe were the Schools of the Prophets in <hi>Shiloh, Ramoth gilead, Jericho, Bethel,</hi> and <hi>Mount Carmell,</hi> and the Scholars there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of were called the ſons of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, 1 Sam. 9.10, 5. 2 King. 2.3. &amp; 4.25. &amp; 6.2. And it is worthy obſervation, that <hi>Samuel</hi> was Maſter of the School of the Prophets at <hi>Nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth</hi> near <hi>Ramah</hi> at ſuch time as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> fled from the preſence of <hi>Saul,</hi> 1 Sam. 19.20. And ſuch a School
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119643:52"/>as this <hi>Gamaliel</hi> kept, of whom <hi>Paul</hi> declares himſelf to have been taught like a childe the knowledge of the Law as well as other learning, Act. 22.3. and as theſe Schools were among the Jewes, ſo we ſhall finde them in the Chriſtian Churches: <hi>Euſebius</hi> reporteth out of <hi>Philo Judeus,</hi> that there was at <hi>Alexandria</hi> in <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> an ancient School founded by <hi>Ptolemeus,</hi> famous throughout the world; when <hi>Mark</hi> the Evangeliſt preached the Goſpel there, he turned the ſame into a Chriſtian School; the which did afterward ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue; and in it <hi>Origen</hi> was School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter, and when by reaſon of the multitude of the Scholars that reſort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> found himſelf not able to perform the duty, he choſe <hi>Hera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clas</hi> (a man expert in holy Scripture and ſtudious of divine things, very eloquent, and not ignorant of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy) to be his Uſher, fellow-helper, dividing the company, did appoint him to initiate and enter them in the faith, and he himſelf did teach them that were riper, not
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119643:53"/>only in Philoſophy Geometry and other liberal Arts, but in divine things alſo. So <hi>Pamphilus</hi> a Chriſtian Philoſopher did ordain at <hi>Ceſarea,</hi> a famous School both for divine and humane learning: and <hi>Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen</hi> doubted not to call the School at <hi>Athens</hi> a golden parent of all ſpeech and learning. To this reaſon we might add an evidence of God's conſtituting of Schools as fountains of Chriſtian Religion from Satans enmity againſt the ſame, expreſſed by the cruel martyrdome of famous <hi>Caſſianus</hi> of <hi>Forum</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> by his Scholars at the cruel command of the Emperor, and the putting down of ſuch Schools by <hi>Julian</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate in his devilliſh deſign of rooting out all Chriſtian Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Schoolmaſters ought to Catechize, becauſe <hi>it is impoſſible for youth, to go well forward in vertue and good manners (the end of all learning) unleſſe they be well inſtructed in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Religion and Doctrine of Chriſt:</hi> for the fear of the Lord is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of wiſdome.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:119643:53"/>
            <p>Fourthly, Without Catechizing, <hi>godly parents do miſſe of the end of all their care and charges in ſetting their children to ſchool, which is to be educated in the fear of the Lord, and inſtructed in the true Religion:</hi> which neglected, a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan were as good as a Chriſtian, a Papiſt as good as a Proteſtant School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter for them.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, In not Catechizing, <hi>they tranſgreſſe the Law of Church and all Chriſtian Common-wealth:</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires that a Schoolmaſter ſhould ſubſcribe to ſound Doctrine: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ought chiefly to teach Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>Prayers (which we ſuppoſe to be in Chriſtian Schools (unleſſe they will come ſhort of Paganiſh tutors, who uſed to begin their leſſons with invocation to their gods) cannot but be profaned and uſed unreverently, where Catechizing is negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted:</hi> becauſe through want of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, the youth underſtand not the duty in generall, nor petition in particular, and ſo it is unto them as in an unknown tongue.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſhewed you the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119643:54"/>why Miniſters and Schoolmaſters ſhould Catechize, we come now to conſider the Reaſons why this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is to be performed by Parents and Maſters of families, which are briefly theſe:</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>God commands and commends it in them,</hi> in Deut. 4.9. &amp; 6.7. &amp; 11.19. <hi>Thou ſhalt teach thy children, thy ſons and thy ſons ſons;</hi> in Epheſ. 6.4. <hi>Parents are required to bring up their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the inſtruction and information of the Lord:</hi> beſides that command in Prov. 22.6. <hi>Train up a childe in his youth:</hi> and this duty hath been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in <hi>Abraham,</hi> in Gen. 14.14. &amp; 18.19. and the effect of it in <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That they may (as much as in them lies) help forward the regeneration of their children:</hi> to whom they have conveyed an evill and corrupted na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. To this Catechizing is ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly helpful by laying in the ſoul the Word of God, by which is conveighed the immortal ſeed, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming them in the Doctrine of God, ſinfull nature and their
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119643:54"/>own covenant with God in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That they may <hi>propagate Religion to poſterity according to their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> in Deut. 4.9. Gen. 18.18. un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which end, as we before noted, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizing is ſingularly inſtrumental.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That they may <hi>prepare their families even in the time of their youth to bear witneſſe to the truth,</hi> unto the confuſion of the enemies thereof, as did the Children of <hi>Merindoll:</hi> nay under the moſt exquiſite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to rejoyce in and encourage to patient conſtancy in the faith of Chriſt: for this hath added much force unto the truth of God in all ages, that it hath not only been ſealed with the bloud of men of age and gray hairs, but alſo youth, even of Infants, who have been unmovably fixed in it: which how could they have been, or their parents encourage them to it, and endear them to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by it, if they had not been well inſtructed in the Doctrine of Chriſt, and their Parents diſcharged their duty in Catechizing them betimes:
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:119643:55"/>of the which we ſhall finde ſeverall inſtances in the third perſecution un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperour, we read of <hi>Symphoriſa a godly matron martyred with her ſeven children:</hi> and <hi>Sophia with her three children:</hi> alſo in the fourth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution under <hi>Antoninus Verus,</hi> we read of the <hi>ſeven children of</hi> Felicitas <hi>cruelly and diverſly martyred before her eyes, her ſelf chearfully alſo ſealing the truth with death:</hi> ſo alſo <hi>a woman of Syria and her two daughters,</hi> and <hi>Athanaſia and her three daughters:</hi> What ſhall I ſay of <hi>young Eulatia,</hi> and others un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Heathens, beſides the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of a boy of eight or nine years old well inſtructed by his father: <hi>John Fatty,</hi> who was by <hi>Bonner</hi> cruelly whipped for his profeſſion: What ſhall I ſay of <hi>Vitalis,</hi> who ſuffered with his <hi>godly Maſter Agrico:</hi> of <hi>John Leaf, an Apprentice,</hi> who was with Mr. <hi>Bradford burned at the nineteenth year of his age:</hi> of <hi>Tho. Hinſhaw,</hi> cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whipped in <hi>Bonner</hi>'s garden for the Truth? but above all I cannot paſſe with ſilence <hi>the Childe</hi> which wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed the truth of God with <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:119643:55"/>Romanus</hi> when but <hi>ſeven years of age,</hi> who having witneſſed the profeſſion of it under cruel whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and at laſt having his skin pull'd off his head, was thus encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by his godly Mother: <hi>My childe thirst after the cup of which the Children of</hi> Bethleem <hi>did drink; remember</hi> Iſaac<hi>'s obedience unto death: ſuffer a little my childe, thou ſhalt anon go to him that will cover thy naked head with a crown of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall glory:</hi> and when after with a ſmiling countenance he had appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved himſelf invincible by ſuffering torments, and was cruelly beheaded to the grief of the beholders, and great joy of the Mother, only ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by with dry eyes ſinging to Gods glory,
<q>
                  <l>All praiſe with heart and voice,</l>
                  <l>O Lord, we yeeld to thee,</l>
                  <l>To whom the death of all thy Saints,</l>
                  <l>we know moſt dear to be.</l>
               </q> This conſtancy of the childe, and comfort of the Mother, muſt needs witneſſe the truth of his anſwer to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:119643:56"/>the Captain that he <hi>ſucked in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt with his mothers milk:</hi> and much enforce this Reaſon for Maſters of families Catechizing.</p>
            <p>The fifth and laſt Reaſon why Maſters of families ſhould Catechize, may be this, <hi>That they may preſerve the Church of God in their houſes,</hi> faithfully diſcharge the Prophetical office (to which they are redeemed by Jeſus Chriſt) in inſtructing their families in matters of Faith and obedience, whereby they are enabled to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their ſeveral duties towards God and man, that they may ſweeten relation, and the performances of their prieſtly office in prayer and praiſes to be preſented with faith and fear, with fervor and feeling, whileſt by diligent Catechizing they are enabled to do all with knowledge and underſtanding.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſhewed you who muſt Catechize, we ſhall briefly ſhew you what they muſt do in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this duty, before we ſhew you who muſt be Catechized.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>The Catechiſm ready and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techized
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119643:56"/>preſent, they muſt</hi> (as in every other Ordinance of God) <hi>begin with hearty and earneſt prayer</hi> to the moſt wiſe God for his bleſſing on this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine exerciſe, that it may tend to the edification of all concerned in it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Propound the queſtions, and require an audible anſwer thereunto:</hi> for it is moſt expedient that the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm be by queſtion and anſwer, as was before noted.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Audibly repeat the queſtion and anſwer,</hi> that ſuch as ſtand by may be ſure to hear, obſerve, and have it the better imprinted in their mindes and memories.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Cauſe the Catechized accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their capacities to prove the ſeveral propoſitions expreſſed in the queſtions and anſwers,</hi> by ſome ſutable places of Scripture, that they may be able to diſcern them to be the truths of God grounded on his Word.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, according to their ſeveral abilities, and in their proper places, they muſt <hi>explain the ſeveral propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that they may the better be underſtood,</hi> and the heart be the more affected
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:119643:57"/>with the ſame, and alſo take notice of the principal errors that do oppoſe them: they muſt perform the whole duty cheerfully and reverently, as becomes an ordinance of God; prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the forward, encouraging the willing, patiently bearing with the weak, and gravely admoniſhing the unruly.</p>
            <p>We come now to ſhew you who muſt be Catechized: in the conſideration whereof, we ſhall firſt ſhew who were wont to be Catechized in the primitive times: and then who amongſt us ought to ſubject themſelves to this duty.</p>
            <p>In the primitive times they did uſually Catechize two ſorts, <hi>the one before, and the other after Baptiſm:</hi> thoſe that were Catechized before Baptiſm, were <hi>Heathens converted from their Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm to the knowledge of the true God,</hi> who before they were received into the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of Jeſus Chriſt, were Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed. <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> in his ſecond Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie for the Chriſtians, declares, that if any Heathen man deſired to be received
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119643:57"/>into the fellowſhip of the Church, he was firſt Catechized in the principles of Religion; and then hearing further the Word of God, as it were the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the covenant: afterward came into the face of the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and made a profeſſion thereof promiſing their obedience thereunto, and ſo they were baptized, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived as members: ſuch an one was <hi>Auguſtine, when converted from Manichiſm,</hi> he was Catechized, and then Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, in which time of his Catechiſm he wrote many books: ſo <hi>Ambroſe was in his Catechiſm and not baptized when choſen Biſhop of Millaine:</hi> ſuch as theſe were the <hi>Burgundians</hi> whom <hi>Socrates</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares to have been ſeven daies in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizing, and baptized in the eighth day: <hi>Jerom ad Pannachium</hi> makes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch as were in his daies Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techized forty daies, and then bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed: in <hi>Tertullian's daies</hi> they did Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techize till Eaſter or Whitſontide, and then baptize: in a word, ſuch as theſe were Catechumeni and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices ſent away from the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:119643:58"/>
            <p>The ſecond ſort Catechized, were <hi>the children of the faithful, who had been baptized in their Infancy:</hi> who when they came to years of diſcretion were taught how great things the Lord had done for them and for their forefathers, in receiving them into his covenant; the which things when they had learned, and were able to render a reaſon of the ſame, they were brought into the Congregation, and made a profeſſion of their Faith, promiſing obedience thereunto; and ſo in their own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons renewed covenant with God, and were confirmed members of the Church, as <hi>Deodate</hi> infers from Heb. 6.2. Laying on of hands: and ſo alſo <hi>Calvin, Beza, Hemingius,</hi> and others on the place.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſhewed who were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to be Catechized in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times and Churches, we may take notice amongſt us all being baptized in their infancy, we are not in capacity of admitting that diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and therefore we muſt in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reſolve, that <hi>thoſe and all thoſe
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119643:58"/>that are ignorant of or not well inſtructed in the main and fundamental grounds of Religion and the Christian Doctrine, muſt be Catechized,</hi> whether they be young or old, rich or poor, high or low, married or unmarried; for ignorance is alwaies the ground of this exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, and therefore whileſt age, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and condition cannot expell or diſpenſe with ignorance in any, they cannot exempt any from this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing ordinance of God: but if indeed we might conclude thoſe that are of years to have been Catechized, then we only make <hi>youth the ſubject of this exerciſe,</hi> who would be put to it by their parents as ſoon as they are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of any thing elſe, and be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in the Church ſo ſoon as they can quietly abide, and give a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable account of their capacity to be inſtructed; that ſo being betime ſeaſoned with this ſpiritual liquor, they may alwaies retain the ſavour of it: and <hi>trained up in it in the daies of his youth,</hi> they may not <hi>depart from it when they are old,</hi> Prov. 22.6. that thereby the Word of God may grow
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:119643:59"/>up with them as <hi>a light unto their feet, and lanthorn their paths,</hi> in directing them to mortifie luſt betimes, to avoid diſobedience to parents, unthriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, idleneſſe and vanity, and other profaneneſſe, to which youth is very prone and ſubject; and to teach them to remember their Creator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, know their duty to God, their parents and others, and when infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with youthful luſt, to conſider that for all things they muſt come to Judgement.</p>
            <p>But more particularly <hi>children and youth</hi> ought to be exerciſed in this ordinance of Catechizing, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove themſelves the ſubjects of this exerciſe for theſe ſpeciall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: That,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Covenant to them confirmed in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm may be underſtood and improved:</hi> want of Catechizing makes Baptiſm ineffectual; the Jewes by Catechizing made their children to underſtand the nature of Circumciſion and the Paſſeover, and covenant thereby ſealed: Confirmation of children was uſed, when by Catechizing they were
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:119643:59"/>able perſonally to claim and engage in the covenant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Counſell unto duty may be ready at hand:</hi> Children as ſoon as they can act their reaſon, are ingaged to duty to God, Eccleſ. 12.1. <hi>Remember thy Creator in the daies of thy youth:</hi> and Catechizing acquaints them with it. I have before noted <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and <hi>Abel</hi>'s ſacrifice to be the fruit of Catechizing: how could King <hi>Joſiah</hi> at ſixteen year old <hi>ſeek the God of</hi> David, <hi>and at twenty years old zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly deſtroy Idolatry,</hi> if he had not been well Catechized? and how ſhould King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth his zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous reſiſtance of Popiſh ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, have proclaimed more Divinity in his finger then in Biſhop <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi>'s head, if he had not well ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Catechiſm? And as they owe duty to God, ſo to men, to their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents obedience, to their elders in age or office reverence, which they are counſelled in by Catechizing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Curbe may grow up with their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions:</hi> a mention of coming to judgement, gives a check to youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119643:60"/>luſt, to the young mans <hi>rejoycing in his youth, and taking his pleaſure,</hi> Eccleſ. 11.9. A well Catechized <hi>Joſeph</hi> will in childhood out of enmity to impiety complain of brethrens miſcarriages, Gen. 37.9. an inlightned conſcience will be able to diſpute with the Devill, and ſilence ſuggeſtions unto ſin.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Change in their nature and diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be wrought:</hi> the work of grace is not in any by natural generation, nor infuſed by any extraordinary inſpiration; it muſt therefore be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in the uſe of ordinary means, whereof none ſute infant capacity as Catechizing; by this the word that <hi>incorruptible ſeed by which we are born again,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.23.</note> is implanted in them to the informing judgement, perſwading the will, and transforming na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Capacity exerciſed in Chriſtianity may be enlarged:</hi> We are moſt capable of the art or trade in which we were trained young; our children can beſt apprehend, judge, diſcourſe of, and invent thoſe things about which they
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:119643:60"/>ſpent their youthfull years: if then they were but exerciſed in principles of Religion and Doctrines of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, they would more readily underſtand, diſcourſe and judge of them when they come to years: the great dexterity of the Jewes in the doctrines of the Scriptures, was the reſult of their Catechiſm: the ready anſwers of the children of <hi>Merindoll,</hi> and the renown<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d childe which ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered with <hi>Romanus,</hi> was no other then the effect of capacity exerciſed in Catechizing.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That they may <hi>continue a ſtable courſe in profeſſion and practiſe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity:</hi> A veſſell when old, retains the ſavour of the liquor with which it was ſeaſoned when new,
<note place="margin">Horace.</note> 
               <hi>Quae ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel eſt imbuta recens ſervabit odorem, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith the Poet, as the reaſon why youth muſt be inſtructed in beſt things: and God teacheth us to <hi>train up a childe in the way he ſhould go, and when he is old, he will not depart from it:</hi> cuſtome doth obdurate in any way, and in waies of piety ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles to withſtand temptation: the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119643:61"/>tree when it is old, ſtands againſt all ſtrength and ſtormes as it was bent when young: <hi>Paul</hi> perſwades <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> to continue in the things he lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, his perſwaſive is that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from a ſucking childe he had known the Scriptures, 2 Tim. 3.14, 15.</p>
            <p>I have ſhewed you ought to be Catechized, and why children are in ſpecial to be the ſubjects of this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe: I ſhall briefly ſhew how they muſt carry in it, and ſo paſſe to the application: As to their carriage that are to be catechized, note theſe rules.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They muſt with all cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and conſtancy ſit under Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing as an ordinance of God, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for their eternal good, not being diſcouraged by any reproaches of the wicked, nor diverted by any temptation whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They muſt with all eager dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence commit to memory all the principles and heads of Chriſtian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine commended and committed to them, not breaking off from the work on any ſenſe of diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119643:61"/>in, or indiſpoſition to the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They muſt be alwaies ready with an holy boldneſſe, to give a reaſon of the hope that is in them to every one that asketh.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They muſt with all reverence and modeſty give audible and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct anſwers to the ſeveral queſtions propounded.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That they may not loſe the end in uſing the means they muſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently ſtudy the anſwers they do repeat, obſerve the queſtions to which they anſwer, reſolve the queſtion and anſwer into entire and diſtinct pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, hearken with all meekneſſe and reverence to the inſtructing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, conſult annexed Scriptures, obſerve their pertinency to prove the principles, and (according to their capacities) commend all to Gods bleſſing by prayer; hereby they will take off the ſcandal caſt on Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, and make it to appear their faith is not pinn'd to another mans ſleeve, but they ſee with their own eyes, aſſent to principles they underſtand,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119643:62"/>and are ready to contend for thoſe Doctrines of the truth of which they are clearly and fully convinced.</p>
            <p>Having thus laid before you the doctrinal conſideration of this Truth, and I hope informed your judgements in the great neceſſity of ſuch a duty in the Church of God, I ſhall now briefly ſuggeſt the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement or application thereof, for the exciting of your affections towards the ſame: and firſt it is uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to information of judgement in theſe truths.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Catechizing is not an exerciſe of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency, but of poſitive neceſſity in the Church of God:</hi> men may not chooſe whether they will inſtruct or be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the principles of Religion and foundations of the Doctrine of God, and perſwade themſelves they do well, if they exerciſe and ſubmit to ſuch inſtruction, but ſin not if they refuſe or neglect the ſame; for if there be (as I hope you ſee) a divine ſtamp on this exerciſe, as an ordinance of God morally and not ceremonially binding, it muſt needs impoſe an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:119643:62"/>and undeniable duty: the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents among the Jewes might not conceive themſelves at liberty in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of conſcience, whether they would teach their <hi>children and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens children</hi> the waies and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the Lord, or no; neither yet the children might think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at liberty to chooſe or refuſe ſubjection unto ſuch inſtruction, whileſt God had enjoyned the ſame as duty: neither yet may Chriſtian parents under the Goſpell chooſe or refuſe the bringing up their families in the nurture and fear of the Lord, by this childiſh way of Catechizing, nor yet children chooſe or refuſe ſubjection to the ſame, whileſt it appears to be an Ordinance of Gods preſcription. And what is thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced concerning parents, holds good concerning Schoolmaſters and Miniſters, according to their relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and in their proper places: Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters may not think they have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged paſtoral duty, when they have preached once or twice a week and neglected this exerciſe, but muſt
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:119643:63"/>know that it is abſolute and undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able duty for them to ſee that all ſuch under their charge as are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the principles of Religion be therein Catechized; and then peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple muſt know it their duty, willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſubject to the ſame: the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical perſwaſion did dictate abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute duty of feeding babes with milk, as well as ſtrong men with ſtrong meat; of laying the foundation of God, as well as building up to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; of diſciples to be exerciſed in and prepared by principles to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive higher doctrines; which was the undoubted ground of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving the Chriſtian Doctrine into Catechetical heads and conſtitution of Catechizing Schools, and order in, the Chriſtian Churches: nay, moreover had inſtruction in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Religion been a matter of indifferency and not of duty, the neglect thereof had not been a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reprehenſive and chargeable on the <hi>Hebrews</hi> as a matter of iniquity. I fear my brethren, it is a too generally received fancy (as well among ſuch
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:119643:63"/>as ſhould catechize, as ſuch as ſhould be catechized) that Catechizing is <hi>good,</hi> but not <hi>neceſſary; commendable</hi> where it is uſed, but not <hi>duty:</hi> this fear may be juſtly grounded on the neglect thereof; nay on childrens and ſervants refuſing ſubjection to ſuch waies when thereunto called, not only by their Miniſters but Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and Maſters: nay in affirming that though it is good, yet it hath not any ground in Scripture: it were well if the <hi>lukewarmneſſe</hi> of ſome in it, and the <hi>perverſneſſe</hi> of ſome to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it, did not lead them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine this exerciſe to be <hi>iniquity,</hi> and denominate it the <hi>Antichriſtian weapon of the late Aſſembly;</hi> but whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſeriouſly conſiders the care of the Biſhops, the conſtant pains of Catechizers, the cheerful ſubmiſſion of Chriſtians (of all ages, ſexes, ranks, and degrees) to this way of inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the continued practiſe of the primitive times of the Chriſtian Churches, ſeconded with the Canons of Councels, conſtitutions of all Church aſſemblies, compoſed Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſms;
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:119643:64"/>conſcientious diſcharge of the duty by the moſt faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and ſervants of God in all the ſucceeding ages of the Church to this day, muſt conclude it to have been apprehended as abſolute duty: which appearing to be a Goſpel ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, yet to be uſed amongſt us and the Churches of God that ſhall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, muſt be accordingly continued, not as a thing of indifferency, and that may be done, but of neceſſity, and that muſt be done.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It may inform us that <hi>ſubjection unto Catechizing in the principles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, is not baſe and ſhamefull, but good and honourable, not with bluſhing, but boldneſſe to be undertaken:</hi> I know not what madneſſe poſſeſſeth mens brains, to make modeſty the main obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this duty; may we not ſee ſuch as are not aſhamed to be <hi>ignorant,</hi> aſhamed by this way to be <hi>inſtructed?</hi> nay and to note it as a ground of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and deriſion, even by laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and digitation, to ſuch as ſubject unto the ſame, as if God had ſtamped divine authority on ſuch ordinances
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:119643:64"/>as might not with modeſty and honour be exerciſed: or had cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for ſuch duties in which his Church and ſervants might not be ſeen without ſhame: Is any Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell ordinance to be declined as ſhamefull and contemptible by ſuch as would be called Chriſtians and Goſpel profeſſors? Did the Apoſtle ever upbraid or leave it as the brand of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> that they were Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techized and ſubjected to this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, or not rather that they had not been ſufficiently Catechized, and made ſuch proficiency in this School and leſſon as they ought to have done? Was it a ſhame for Chriſt to be found among the Catechumeniſts of the Jewes? Could not the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles anſwer without bluſhing to Chriſt his <hi>Whom do ye ſay that I am?</hi> Was it the ſhame of <hi>Theophilus, Apollos,</hi> and others, that they had been Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techized? I finde the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſtigmatizing the Jewes with not practiſing Catechetical heads and rules, as a note of their perpetual in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy; but never with being Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chized,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:119643:65"/>which had been their glory, and now was the great aggravation of their iniquity. Nay is it not the everlaſting renown of the Schools at <hi>Athens</hi> and <hi>Alexandria,</hi> that they were Schools of Catechizing and good learning? Did wiſe Philoſophers, and honourable Senators, and reverend fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Church, when becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtians, ſubmit with ſhame unto this exerciſe? Is not the name of <hi>Origen</hi> famous in the Church for his Catechizing? Is it not recorded to the glory of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> that he was in his Catechiſm, when called to the charge of the Church at <hi>Millaine?</hi> Let men therefore conſider, it may be a ſhame to want Catechizing, but it muſt be our honour to ſubmit to this exerciſe and be Catechized: and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall make it a brand of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to be Catechized, to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of doing duty themſelves, and deride others for their cheerful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge thereof; let it be their brand, that they have through ignorance vilified and deſpiſed a Goſpel exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe; and let the people know and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:119643:65"/>ſettle it in their judgements, that Catechizing being a Goſpel exerciſe is good and honourable.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Uſe of the point is to reprove: ſeeing that Catechizing is Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, a Goſpel exerciſe to be uſed in the Churches of Jeſus Chriſt, it doth juſtly beſpeak matter of blame and rebuke for the <hi>general neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of this exerciſe in the midſt of us in theſe reforming daies:</hi> is it not almoſt laid aſide in congregations and families, as if it had been a tradition of men, rather then an inſtitution of God, a Prelatical fancy and imagination to vaniſh with them and the ceremonies as unſutable for times of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? Oh Chriſtians, is divine ſtamp done away from this exerciſe, that it is done away from practice? is Goſpel direction no guidance to this action, that it is laid aſide by eminent profeſſors of the Goſpel? are there in the Churches of God no ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects for it, that it is ſo ſilent? nay is it not ſad to ſee, and may we not with ſhame and ſorrow conſider igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, error, lukewarmneſſe, to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:119643:66"/>Religion and contempt of the Goſpel, ſo to increaſe as to caſt off (if not caſt out) this inſtructing, initiating, grounding exerciſe? Is it any marvel to finde men Scepticks in Religion, now beleeving this, now that, who were never taught nor learned the principles of Chriſtian Doctrine and ſtanding verities neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be beleeved unto ſalvation? can we wonder to ſee ſouls ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affectionate to piety and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to act the duties thereof pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitately, and irregularly, and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly fall off when we remember that they have no principles fixed in their mindes to guide their practiſe and ſupport their ſpirits? ſhall we think it ſtrange to finde painfull preaching little to profit, when we conſider Catechizing hath not laid the foundation, on which preaching higher doctrines ſhould build? if the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> non-proficiency under this exerciſe made them uncapable of inſtruction and edification by higher Doctrines, what capacity can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected in thoſe Churches where this
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:119643:66"/>duty is wholly neglected? have we not cauſe to fear Popiſh and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous doctrines catechetically pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, eaſily to captivate poor ſouls from very fundamental truths, whereof for want of Catechizing they muſt needs be ignorant? In a word, my brethren,
<note place="margin">In the <hi>Cracovian</hi> and <hi>Bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſms.</note> is it not ſad to ſee, and may we not with ſhame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the light of nature teaching, and the care of men purſuing all Arts and Sciences by principles, axioms and ſtanding verities: and only Chriſtian Doctrine neglected to be thus taught and learned? did not the paſt ages of the Church of God commonly both teach and learn the Doctrine of God by this exerciſe, as the way of the Lords preſcription: and ſhall we in this age neglect and omit it; Let all therefore ſubjected to the guilt of this great iniquity of neglecting this Goſpel exerciſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ſame ſeriouſly, and take to themſelves this reproof thus juſtly exhibited, and reflecting in ſpecial on theſe two ſorts of men.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Such who by vertue of their places
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:119643:67"/>ſhould, but do not call to Catechizing ſuch of their relations as are under their charge and tuition in the Lord:</hi> Miniſters, Schoolmaſters and Maſters of fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, who can live from year to year without once calling to their rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to ſeek knowledge and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, without counſelling and inſtructing them in the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals of Religion: without comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and by the authority with which God hath inveſted them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling ſubjection to this duty: I have before ſhewed, that it is the duty of ſuch to Catechize, yet how many ſhall we finde neglecting the ſame, if not many Miniſters (as I fear too many) contenting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with their preaching to peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of years, and never calling for the lambs and young ones of their flock, to receive inſtruction and be fed with milk of Chriſtian principles; yet I fear Schoolmaſters generally ſo neglective of calling on their Scholars to learn and give account of the ABC of Chriſtianity, the ſpecial rules of Goſpel Doctrine,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:119643:67"/>the axioms of truth and true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whileſt they lay out their power and authority in teaching the firſt rules of Arts and Sciences. And Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of families I may (with more confidence then I delight in) charge to have left their children and ſervants at liberty to learn or not to learn, to be Catechized or not to be Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chized: How many are there, that if their children and ſervants of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves will learn and do gain know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the principles of Religion, will not blame them, nay will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them for it, and take comfort in it, whileſt yet themſelves leave them to liberty to do what they liſt, neither commanding them to learn, nor calling for an account of their diligence therein? whereby in the moſt families Catechizing is a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, unacquainted becauſe unuſed: ignorance is nouriſhed, and when good natures are called by their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to be Catechized, though they learn, they are aſhamed to anſwer, to give an account of what they have learned, becauſe unaccuſtomed
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:119643:68"/>ſo to do: when we conſider humane nature ſo ſubject to novelty, as not without difficulty to be kept up with conſtancy in any way, though never ſo good; ſo indiſpoſed to the things of God and the ſoul, as to be at enmity with the dictates of, and directions unto piety: to be defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of liberty, and to be looſe from every duty, and obſerve the golden reigns of ſoveraignty to be thrown on the youthfull neck, which ſenſible thereof, can wantonly run off its due courſe, and the due autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity with which God hath inveſted ſuperiours for the keeping up to duty to be ſuſpended: ſhall we admire to ſee Catechizing neglected, ignorance nouriſhed, or think it ſtrange for Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters many times to call families to anſwer their Catechiſms, and have ſeats and pillars ſooner then many children and ſervants to give anſwer? However ſuch are not ignorant who ſhould be Catechized, yet we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but charge the guilt on ſuch who have authority and ought in duty to bring them to Catechizing,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:119643:68"/>and prepare them for the ſame by keeping to it in their families, but do not: for from youth at liberty we can expect no other then a neglect of duty, and therefore give me leave to affect your hearts with this ſin by laying before you theſe few conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Duty is neglected,</hi> whileſt you do not Catechize your ſelves, ſuch as are under your charge, and call upon them to learn; nay in thy place com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and according to thy autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity compell to be Catechized. That it is your duty to Catechize, I have before ſhewed; if that it be not done, duty is neglected: indiſpoſition and averſeneſſe of the children and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily will be no excuſe to thee; for hath God put the rod of correction any more into thy hand in vain, then he hath put the ſword into the hand of the Magiſtrate? hath he not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained thee in thy ſphere, to be a terror to ſuch as do evill, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courager to the good? hath he not put in ſubjection to thee ſuch as he hath placed under thy charge? doth
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:119643:69"/>he not require from thy hand that thou and thy houſe ſhould ſerve the Lord? It is the good note of learned <hi>Zanchy</hi> on the fourth Command, that it doth not command, remember to keep holy the Sabbath, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade thy children and ſervant to keep it holy, implying it is the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Maſter and father to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell to the keeping the Sabbath; and therefore it is ſaid thou <hi>ſhalt do it,</hi> and thy ſon, and thy man-ſervant, and maid-ſervant; for God and Nature takes it for granted, that the ſubject family conform to the command of the Maſter of it. Thoſe ſeveral com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands in Scripture of teaching our children and houſhold to know the Law of the Lord, and to train them up in the nurture of the Lord; muſt neceſſarily imply the laying out or exerciſe of authority, to compel their averſeneſſe unto duty, and command their attendance on, and diligence in inſtructing means; and not to teach them if they be willing, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect it when they are unwilling: and the Goſpell command to chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:119643:69"/>obedience to their parents, to hear their inſtructions, to bear their reproofs, and to obey their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands (as <hi>Zanchy</hi> notes) muſt needs imply a parents power and duty to inſtruct, reprove, and command; and therefore to cloſe up this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, mourn for your ſubjection to old <hi>Eli</hi> his ſin of ſlack rebukes and neglect of paternall authority: and let me tell you, that I do beleeve the neglect of paternall power and due exerciſe of that authority, God hath given to call and compell to duty, will not be found the leaſt of relative ſins in the day of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Secondly, You are <hi>degenerated from the practiſe of the people of God in paſt ages,</hi> whoſe reſolution was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for themſelves but theirs alſo, that they ſhould ſerve the Lord. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs and people of God among the Jews did teach and command their ſeed to ſerve God: thus did <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> as a dying man charge <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> his ſon, and ſo others whom I have before mentioned: and I have
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:119643:70"/>before noted, that God exceedingly extols <hi>Abraham</hi> for this very reaſon, that he knew he would uſe his pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall power, to ſee his children and houſhold to keep Gods waies: on which words a reverend Divine notes, that <hi>Abraham</hi> did not leave his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and ſervants to their own ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, their own counſels, their own luſts; nay he would not allow them in ſuch a liberty, as would have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticed them into the worſt kinde of bondage. Oh conſider brethren, is paternall power any leſſe now under the Goſpell then before, and under the Law? or are not we more dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated from the pious property of authoritative acting zeal for duty, then they were whoſe poſterity we profeſſe to be, and whoſe practiſe we would be thought to follow?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, You <hi>deal worſe for the ſoul,</hi> then for <hi>the bodies of your relations,</hi> in that you will leave them to liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in reſpect of the waies of God, when you limit them in matters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the outward man: How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men will compell their ſervants
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:119643:70"/>and children to this and that way of ſerving them, though they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo averſe, that yet will let them ſtudy the waies of God when and how they will; and if averſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, let ſlack their authority, ſet them at liberty and indulge their neglect of duty: many a man will from day to day, and week to week call for accounts of the ſervice done to themſelves, that cannot, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will not from ſabbath to ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath call for an account of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies progreſſe in their Catechiſm, and rudiments of Religion: nay, and will not many men make the rod to caution and command from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the bodies of their children, that can paſſe in ſilence the deſperate dangers to which the ſoul is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected? Will they not many times put out their power to prohibit ſuch company and courſes as may endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger their perſons or eſtates, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their bleſſing charge and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand ſuch and ſuch courſes as may conduce to their ſuppoſed happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? which yet can let their own
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:119643:71"/>genius lead to or from the duties that may advantage the ſoul for ever: O fools and unwiſe, can you think that God gave this power into your hand for your ſelves alone, and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to command for him? and is not the immortall ſouls of your dear relations much better then their mortall bodies? what ſhall be their profit to gain the whole world and loſe the ſoul? but will it not be the ſhame of Chriſtians, that as men of this world, they ſhould be wiſer in their generation then as the children of God?</p>
            <p>But theſe Reproofs are by ſome ſtaved off by ſome Pleas, which they think to be not only ſufficient to acquit them from the charge of ſin, but alſo to juſtifie their neglect, as if it were good and warrantable. Theſe Pleas are ſo weak, that they were not worth taking notice of them: had not notable ignorance and the nice and ſinfull ſcrupuloſity of our times given them ſtrength enough to keep off from poſitive duty; weak Chriſtians but inclining the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:119643:71"/>leaſt to the pretended and much cryed up new lights in our daies: therefore ſuch as they are I ſhall ſet before you with anſwers to them. Whereof the firſt is,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Plea. </seg>1</label> That our way of Catechizing, is a forme asking ſome ſet queſtions, and receiving ſet anſwers to them, and they think all formes unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Apoſtles did deliver to the ſucceeding Miniſters <hi>a form of ſound words,</hi> and gave it in charge that it ſhould be <hi>held faſt,</hi> as did <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi> 2 Tim. 1.13. and was this ſinful and to be condemned? or if ours be a form, is it of unſound words? if ſo, let them make it to appear, we will then lay it aſide; till then, we muſt conclude to charge and caſt off Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techeticall Doctrine becauſe in a form, is not only to condemn the generation of the juſt, but alſo the very Apoſtles of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Ten Commandements are a form, (nay and ſuch a form as is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punged out of theſe mens books, and
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:119643:72"/>exil'd their families) yet God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Jewes to teach them their children, and whet them dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently upon them, as well as keep them in their own hearts, Deut. 6.6, 7. Shall we be afraid to teach our children the ten Commandements, when we finde it to be the leſſon God himſelf hath ſet them? may not we that are Gods Uſhers ſafely teach in the method that our Maſter hath propounded? nay, muſt we not of duty do it? Is it not eminent piety and devout ſcrupuloſity that makes us queſtion and caſt off divine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription? Rather, is it not the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils cavill againſt duty, it is done in a form?</p>
            <p n="3">3. That our Catechiſms are thus in Formes, doth moſt anſwer our main end of Catechizing, which is to teach men and women from their Infancy, to think and ſpeak the ſame things that the Members of the Church may be of one minde and one mouth in the Lord. Certain it is, that the Church never tun'd diſcords in Doctrine ſo high, as ſince we ſtood
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:119643:72"/>at a diſtance from the form of ſound words.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Is it not the Form that conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes the duty, and diſtinguiſheth from other duties? I have before noted, that Catechizing is a teaching by words, a repetition of the ſame ſtrokes, an echo or reiteration of the ſame ſound; ſo that to quarrell at the form, is to quarrell at the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: doth not experience witneſſe, that the crying down of forms is the caſting down of all duties of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick worſhip.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Plea for not Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing is,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Plea. </seg>2</label> That the children Catechized, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing young and not capable of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding what they hear and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat, will but prophane the name of God, by uſing an ordinance in a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functory way, and ſpeaking princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion by rote, without any underſtanding: and in many we may obſerve it doth little good; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny prophane children are in religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous families.</p>
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:119643:73"/>
            <p>I anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The intellectuals of ſome chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are very early ripe, and ſome things are ſo plain and eaſie, that they may be ſoon and eaſily under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood: the ſpeeches that have dropt from ſome children at four, or five, or ſix years of age, do ſufficiently demonſtrate how eaſie ſome truths have been apprehended by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, yea and wrought on the conſciences of little ones.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Stands not this objection con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Scripture, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes children to be the ſubjects of Catechizing: commending <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> for having known and been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Scriptures from his long coats and cradle, 2 Tim. 3.15. Nay, doth not our Saviour juſtifie and defend the little children who cryed Hoſanna to him at his riding into <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 21.16, 17.</note> yet it is more than probable, they underſtood not what they cryed, but only accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the multitude, and according to the objection, ſhould have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for it, as the Phariſees de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired:
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:119643:73"/>have not theſe pretended pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſcruplers need of a <hi>Solomons Be not righteous over much;</hi> and the check of a <hi>Peters</hi> viſion, Act. 10.15. What God hath cleanſed call not thou common?</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is more danger of both preſent and future prophanation of Gods Name by ſwearing, curſing, prophanation of Sabbaths, &amp;c. for want of Catechizing: principles of Religion are a curbe to corruption: &amp; the light kindled in the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding when young may grow up and be a ſtrong reſtraining, if not renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing light; and if prophaneneſſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail much in catechized children, what muſt it do in the uncatechized who have no principles of death, judgement and hell, to curb or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain them? certainly ſuch muſt be drowned by the overflowings of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This Plea doth not only bar us from Catechizing children, but all kinde of inſtructing elder perſons known to be wicked and prophane; for there is more likelihood that ſuch will prophane holy things, and yet no Miniſter is to take the prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:119643:74"/>of his hearers as a ſufficient diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge from his duty, but perſiſt in inſtructing even thoſe that oppoſe themſelves to ſee if God will at any time give them repentance to the acknowledgement of the truth, 2 Tim. 2.25. The prophanation of Gods Name is not the proper reſult of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; but the accidental corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of a wicked heart: and if ſuch effects ſhall diſcharge from duty, what duty ſhall be diſcharged? the word of God may prove the ſavour of death to death, yet it muſt be diſpenſed both by preaching and Catechizing, and the diſpenſers are to God a ſweet ſavour.</p>
            <p>Having noted the reproof againſt ſuperiors for not calling and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding ſuch as are under their charge unto <hi>Catechizing:</hi> we now come to the reproof of <hi>inferiors;</hi> and it is to blame them which have been decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſubjects of Catechizing, for <hi>ſhunning the ſame</hi> as a matter of ſhame: nay many for <hi>ſtouting it out and ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornly refuſing ſubjection to it,</hi> as a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſin. How ſad is it to ſee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny young people ſpending their
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:119643:74"/>time in vanity, and ſtudiouſly lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning things ſcurrilous and profane, yet ſlighting and ſetting at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance the principles of piety and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments of the Doctrine of Chriſt, as if unſutable to their age, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable to be known? nay, much more is it a ſhame to ſee many ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornly reſiſting parental commands, and ſcornfully ſhunning Miniſterial cals to Catechizing, as if they owed no ſubjection to ſuch relations, or were by them ſummoned unto things uncivill and unwarrantable. Let me tell you Chriſtians, a youth igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in principles of Religion, is the ſhame of Chriſtianity, and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall of the reformed Churches: herein we fall ſhort of Heathens, who are ſtudious to educate their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in morality and the worſhip of their Idols, and come behinde the Papiſts, who are diligent in ſtudying their ſuperſtitions: How many are unwilling to be Catechized, that will take on them to teach others? but unto this I ſhall as in the former re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof aggravate their ſin, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:119643:75"/>the Pleas by which they would evade the reproof.</p>
            <p>Let ſuch as ſhun or ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſe ſubjection unto Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing, conſider that in ſo doing they do</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Caſt off divine preſcription:</hi> it hath been noted and proved, that God himſelf is the Author that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Catechizing, and aſſigned all that are ignorant, but in ſpeciall, youth and children to be the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of it; and will youth refuſe and riſe up againſt it? is this your remembrance of God your Creator in the daies of your youth? or did you but ſeriouſly remember your Creator to be a God of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty and power, that may and can require ſubmiſſion to his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, of juſtice and ſeverity that will puniſh every diſobedience and reſiſtance thereof: how could you ſinfully ſlight or ſtubbornly refuſe ſubjection unto Catechizing? If God put a period to your daies under the contempt of his preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions, how perplexed would your
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:119643:75"/>ignorant ſouls be found? how wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to learn and be Catechized if then you might?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Contradict the practice of pious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors,</hi> who have ſubjected to this exerciſe, and herein are become our patterns: Which of all the Saints in Scripture did refuſe or reſiſt Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing? were not theſe the children of Wiſdome, who well knew the duties commanded of God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, nay commodious to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? doth not your ſtubborn re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of, and ſtiffe conteſts againſt ſubjection to this exerciſe, charge the generation of the juſt with folly and vanity?</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Content themſelves to be captivated by Satan, ſubjected to corruption and condemnation:</hi> Ignorance is the Devils chain, and ſin's cords by which the ſoul is taken captive at his will; Catechizing cuts them aſunder: this the thread that leads out of the laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth of confuſion and diſorder, to which we are ſubject by nature: but Satan as the Prince of this world, ſtudies to blind your eyes by keeping
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:119643:76"/>you from and ſetting you againſt the means of inſtruction and illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, leſt the <hi>light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, who is the image of God, ſhould ſhine into you;</hi> hereby your ſtrength ſerves corruption, and your glorious youth is in bondage to Satan: nay, and not only ſo, but condemnation muſt needs juſtly paſſe upon you: for light is come to you, and you love darkneſſe: you have ſouls capable of, and liable to condemnation, and your youth will be no apologie to acquit you; for that God hath by Catechizing ſuted his Word, which is able to ſave the ſoul, unto youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, nay infant capacities; but you have ſlighted or ſtubbornly reſiſted ſubjection to it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Contract on themſelves the guilt of ſtubbornneſſe and diſobedience to ſuperiors,</hi> Miniſters and Chriſtian Parents: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion is as the ſin of Witchcraft, and diſobedience, as iniquity and idolatry; ſo deteſtable was diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to parents, that the diſobedient ſon was to be ſtoned: were this Law in force, how dreadfull would
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:119643:76"/>be the confutation of many who withſtand ſubjection to Catechizing, when thereunto counſelled and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by parents? what obedience can be expected in things civill from ſuch, who reſiſt commands enforced with ſpecial divine authority?</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Cannot ſtand in a ſtorm:</hi> the ſhip cannot ſail ſtedfaſtly in a tempeſt, but roll to and fro, when not well ballanced: Children in underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding muſt needs be like <hi>children toſſed to and fro with every winde of doctrine:</hi> Will not experience witneſſe our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catechized youth, to have wandred from error to error, being led up and down with the <hi>ignis fatuus</hi> of new lights that have appeared? and certainly ſuch as cannot ſtand in the ſtorm of ſeducing doctrines, will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver indure the force of fiery perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution: how ſhall any contend for the faith, in which they have not been Catechized?</p>
            <p>You have ſeen the reproof with its aggravations, we ſhall now anſwer the Pleas made to ſtave off the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:119643:77"/>ſtrength of the reproof, and they are ſuch as are not worth noting, yet ſome of them I ſhall conſider, and they are theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Plea. </seg>1</label> They are willing to be Catechized, and could be content to ſubject themſelves to the Ordinance, were it not they ſhall be accounted ſingular in reviving an unuſefull exerciſe, and ſhall be gazed and laughed at by the reſt of their fellowes, who out of profaneneſſe keep away from it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſo they muſt be alone in the exerciſe.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to this conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Thou maiſt not ſtand alone:</hi> thy example may draw others to be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techized, many are convinced of the duty, and willing to ſet to it, but not perſwaded to be the firſt ſeen at it; deal herein as in your ſports, ſome muſt begin, then all will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If thou be alone and derided, <hi>is it not the lot of the righteous?</hi> doth not Chriſt declare his children to be <hi>for ſigns and for wonders,</hi> in Iſa. 8.18.
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:119643:77"/>and wilt thou be diſcouraged in, or driven from thy duty by the deriſion of the wicked, whileſt it is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon portion of the pious?</p>
            <p n="3">3. To be alone, is <hi>thy honour, and will be thy comfort:</hi> thou ſhalt loſe no credit in the Church, nor comfort at the day of Judgement, by being Catechized alone: Was it not the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Lot</hi> to be alone, in <hi>Sodom?</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> to be alone in the old world? doeſt thou think thou ſhalt ſit down in heaven ſurrounded with penſive thoughts, that thou didſt tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell alone in the way thither? How many men can be glad to drive a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular trade by which to grow rich? canſt not thou then be contented to uſe alone that courſe that will make thee rich in faith?</p>
            <p n="4">4. The uſe of the duty will make thee to <hi>ſee their gazing and laughing at thee to be ridiculous:</hi> whileſt thereby you will be more and more convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of the duty cleared in your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of its indiſpenſable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity: nay ſuck ſweetneſſe and taſte
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:119643:78"/>the abundant benefit thereby acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the ſoul, will plainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince thee, that it is a matter plainly ridiculous in them to deride not only an Ordinance of God, but of abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant advantage to their own ſouls.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>God will laugh at the calamity of ſuch</hi> as ſtand in their ignorance, and ſcorn the means of knowledge and underſtanding, in Prov. 1.22. <hi>How long you ſimple ones, will you love ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city? ſcorners delight in ſcorning, and fools hate knowledge?</hi> and in verſ. 26. <hi>I will laugh at your calamity, and mock when your fear cometh.</hi> Is it not better to be mocked by men then God? do thou thy duty, leave them to bear the burden of their profane deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Plea. </seg>2</label> The ſecond Plea, is that they are ſhamefac'd, could be content to learn the Catechiſm, but are aſhamed to anſwer it in publique, and therefore they do neglect or refuſe it.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to this conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Shame belongs to ſin:</hi> ſin and ſhame were born together into the world;
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:119643:78"/>
               <hi>Adam</hi> in innocency was naked and not aſhamed, but when he had ſinned, ſaw himſelf naked and was aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; whileſt then thou pleadeſt ſhamefacedneſſe, thou chargeſt Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing with ſin, and of that thou haſt cauſe to be aſhamed, for it is Gods preſcription, no humane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, and the holy one of <hi>Iſrael</hi> cannot ſin, neither doth impoſe on men any action of which they ſhould be aſhamed: if God have enjoyned, it is duty, and it is a ſinful ſhame to be aſhamed of duty: thou muſt take heed thy ſhame of duty make not Chriſt aſhamed of thee; for he hath ſaid, <hi>He that ſhall be aſhamed of me or of my words, of him will I be aſhamed when he cometh in the glory of the Father with all his holy Angels,</hi> Mar. 8.39.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Art thou not paſt ſhame in matters of ſin?</hi> canſt thou not ſtudy and ſpeak lewd and laſcivious ſongs? baſe, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure and ribald diſcourſes, that the light of nature bluſheth and is aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to hear uttered? and yet art thou aſhamed to learn the rudiments
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:119643:79"/>of Religion, and Doctrines of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity? modeſty in this nature is madneſſe, ſpiritual madneſſe to be rebuked and blamed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Art thou really and indeed ſhamefaced, thou ſhouldeſt ſet to the duty with the greater reſolution, for that <hi>thy conſtitution becomes unto thee a temptation</hi> unto ſinfull neglect of duty: Satan is apt and ready to lay before temptations from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thee; but none will ſo much prevail and prove ſo difficult to maſter, mortifie, and ſubdue, as thoſe that ſpring from thy conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Doe thy duty when thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty or ſhamefacedneſſe appears re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and irreſiſtible, it is more then probable it will be indulged; ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy thy Catechiſm, though thou anſwer in a corner, better ſo then not at all.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Plea. </seg>3</label> The laſt Plea, is that we could be content to be Catechized, but now we are grown to years, and look towards men and women, and
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:119643:79"/>by reaſon of our age conceive our ſelves to be excuſed, and ſo much the rather for that we have attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſome ripeneſſe of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and are in a better capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of gaining profit by the Word preached and read, then we were when young.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>It is your ſhame to be men and women in years, and children in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding?</hi> Is it not a ſhame to be gotten into your teens, and not able to repeat the Ten Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements: How many children go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond you in knowledge of principles of Chriſtianity?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>So were others when they were Catechized:</hi> as <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſervants: <hi>Theophilus, Apollos, Ambroſe,</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> moſt of the primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: thoſe were not aſhamed when their beards were grown, to be publiquely Catechized.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncatechized thou canſt not well profit by reading or hearing the Word:</hi> for thy knowledge thereby muſt
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:119643:80"/>be immethodicall and confuſed: nay many terms uſed in preaching cannot be underſtood by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catechized; thou maiſt fill thy head with confuſed and indigeſted notions, which will never nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh the heart, and be like the childe which wanting breaſt-milk is big-headed by the Rickets, but very little and weak bodied: and with theſe airy and indigeſted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, thou art puft up with pride, ready to ſtep into the Pulpit, and to preach to others before thou be Catechized, as is the common pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of many Prentices.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt Uſe of the point, is of exhortation to ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours and inferiours in their places, to own, exerciſe, advance and ſubject unto this ordinance of God, <hi>Catechizing:</hi> let me in the Name of the Lord, earneſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat all ſuch as have the charge and overſight of youth, diligently to inſtruct them in, and require a conſtant account of their Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm:
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:119643:80"/>and all ſuch as are in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, with all readineſſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, alacrity and audacity, ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſubject your ſelves to your Catechiſms. Parents and Maſters of families, in your houſes duly uſe your abilities in counſelling, and authority in commanding un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Catechizing, as you make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of duty, or expect comfort in your family; let your houſes be houſes of Catechizing, your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and ſervants be conſtantly Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techized: Schoolmaſters in your Schools be no leſſe carefull and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to teach rudiments of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, then other Arts and Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and inſtruct in Chriſtianity as well as Morality the children com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to your care: let the fame of the School at <hi>Alexandria</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> be the renown of your Schools; Miniſters make conſciences to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter this milk of principles by Catechizing to babes in Chriſt, with no leſſe diligence then to feed men with the meat of higher Doctrines
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:119643:81"/>by conſtant preaching; let not youth upbraid us to have bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed them into a Religion in which we never Catechize or inſtruct them; and whileſt ſuperiors are required to do their duty, let inferiours take heed they do not ſinfully ſlight, or ſtubbornly reſiſt ſubjection to this ordinance of Catechizing, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the perſwading both ſuperiours and inferiours duly to diſcharge their reſpective duties. I need pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound no other motives then what hath been before urged.</p>
            <p>Conſider but the Reaſons of the Doctrine, and if <hi>Excellency may induce, Neceſſity enforce. Antiquity engage, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tility exaſperate,</hi> or <hi>Eaſineſſe and Familiarity excite</hi> to a duty, reject, reſiſt Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing if you can: moreover, reflect on, and revolve in your ſerious thoughts the particular reaſons rendred, why Parents in their families, School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters in their Schools, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in their Congregations muſt Catechize: why the ignorant in generall, and youth or childehood
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:119643:81"/>in ſpeciall are ſubjected to this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance; tell me whether you have not pregnant perſwaſions un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Catechizing? yet that I may not cloſe the Doctrine without ſome heart-moving, ſoul-quickning conſiderations, weigh ſeriouſly theſe ſeverall motives, I deſire to ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt to ſuperiors and inferiors joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſtirre up the one conſtantly to Catechize, the other chearfully to be Catechized.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mot. </seg>1</label> The firſt Motive is, <hi>That principled pious youth is a pleaſure and delight to God,</hi> but provocation and diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure unto Satan: This is that which God cals for in Eccleſ. 12.1. <hi>Remember thy Creator in the daies of thy youth before the daies come wherein thou ſhalt ſay, I have no pleaſure in them.</hi> Wilt thou leave thoſe daies to God of which thou wilt be weary thy ſelf; can God take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in that time which thou canſt take none thy ſelf?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>For des</hi> Sermon of Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing.</note> It is an obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Rabbies on Levit. 1.14. that Turtles may be offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:119643:82"/>in ſacrifice at any age, but Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons when they are young: we ſhould conſider our children are not turtles (that is, Chriſts ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ones) by nature, but are Pige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be dedicated to God when young: and as God cals for a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous principled youth, ſo he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends it, 2 Tim. 3.17. Nay it layeth an engagement on God to communicate his Counſell to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> that he knoweth that he will <hi>command his houſhold and his children that they ſhall keep the way of the Lord,</hi> Gen. 18.17, 19. And whileſt it pleaſeth God, it diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Satan; for <hi>pietas juventutis eſt Diaboli flagellum:</hi> Hence it is he ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounds youth with ſuch variety of temptations unto ſin and obſtruction unto duty.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mot. </seg>2</label> The ſecond Motive, <hi>Pious order is produced in well principled families:</hi> Catechizing counſels every ſoul to their relative and perſonall duties; <hi>Abrahams</hi> family was Catechized, as was before noted: and what a
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:119643:82"/>harmony of duty is to be obſerved in all the parts of the family? his wife is humble and reverent to her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; the Scripture takes ſpeciall notice of <hi>Sarahs calling Abraham Lord,</hi> and propounds her as a pattern of meekneſſe and ſubmiſſion, 1 Pet. 3.6. His ſon <hi>Iſaac</hi> is ſubject and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to his father, chearfully bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the wood on which he ſhould have been ſacrificed; nay ſubjecting his throat to the ſacrificing knife; leaving the choiſe of his wife to his fathers pleaſure: beſides his pious education expreſſeth it ſelf in his daily meditating devotion, Gen. 22 6. &amp; 24.41. &amp; 6.31. So alſo his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <hi>Eliezer</hi> is faithfull to the oath ſworn to his Maſter, and purſueth the ſame with all piety and prudence: ſo that the effect of Catechizing is ſeen in all the members of the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, making it a Church for its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, orderly and pious performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of duty.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mot. </seg>3</label> 3. Catechizing is the <hi>proper means for edifying the Churches of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> God never denied the Infants of
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:119643:83"/>Chriſtian parents admiſſion into his Church; nay ſince his Church was viſible on earth, he owned as Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of it parents and their ſeed; and therefore for the preſervation and due edification of it, ordained Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing conſtantly and lawfully to be uſed, and infants members of the Church to be the ſubjects thereof (as was before noted). By Catechizing the ſap of Chriſtianity is communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the youngeſt ſprouting branches of the Church of God: the great piety of our age is placed in a pretended gathering (but reall ſca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering, by cutting publick ſolemn aſſemblies in private meetings) of Churches, and by many cutting In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants off from the Congregation of Gods people; but ſure I am, that the ſinfull ſuſpenſion of Catechizing, cuts ſhort Chriſtianity, and is likely (if God prevent not) to give us reall cauſe (in the return to infidelity) to gather Churches indeed, and by nip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping buds and ſuffering ſprouts to wither, to replant into the faith of Chriſt, ſuch as muſt bear up his name in the world.</p>
            <pb n="129" facs="tcp:119643:83"/>
            <p n="4">4. Catechizing <hi>prevents the Devils deſign,</hi> by prepoſſeſſing the minde with principles of truth and piety: Satan, as vigilant and ſubtle enemies, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devours to enter the ſoul betimes, and blinde the eye whileſt yet ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to infuſe into the ſoul princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of blaſphemy and prophaneneſſe, knowing that poſſeſſion is eleven points of the Law; &amp; Leaſes of eject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may lay foundations for long and vexatious ſuits: the ſoul poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by Satan will abide many pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull perſwaſions, piercing reproofs, patheticall intreaties, prevailing prayers, and pinching pangs of conſcience, before it will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered: an illuminated conſcience and judgement well informed in the truth, will abide variety of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and aſſaults of Satan, before it will renounce and recede from the true religion. Was not this the ſtratagem of the Councels and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the primitive times againſt the blaſphemous Hereſies of thoſe daies? is not the re-entry of the ſame blaſphemies an engagement to us to
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:119643:84"/>countermine the Devils devices by putting Creeds and Catechiſms in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of our people? nay, is not the vigilancy of Satan and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of his inſtruments in caſting the <hi>Arrian</hi> and <hi>Socinian</hi> Hereſies in Catecheticall forms<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nay in ſcatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abroad the <hi>Cracovian</hi> and <hi>Biddles</hi> Catechiſms, the check of our long ſinfull neglect of Catechizing, and a loud call to ſet to the duty with vigor?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Catechizing <hi>puts into a capacity of living with credit, or dying with comfort,</hi> Catechizing in doctrines of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, doth as well civilize a man as Chriſtianize a ſoul, it inſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s in du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies to be done towards men, as well as towards God: youth not educated in principles of Religion, may live with ſhame and die with ſorrow; for they know not what to do or how to carry themſelves whileſt they live, nor yet wherein to center their hope of future happineſſe when they lie: How many infants, young children, have by Catechizing been famous in their religious lives, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:119643:84"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>terous in duty, conſtant in the faith, and couragious under tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations? and when they have come to die, have cheerfully given up their ſouls to God through Chriſt, in knowledge of whom they have been Catechized? Whileſt youth have ſouls rationall and capable of education, let them not want inſtruction in thoſe things that may make them ſerviceable to God in their genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and whileſt they have ſouls immortall that may be damned or ſaved, when they depart out of their bodies, let them not want Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing in the waies of everlaſting peace.</p>
            <p>Thus then you have ſeen the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine proved, illuſtrated, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, in the application you have been exhorted to the duty, conſider ſeriouſly the duty preſſed on you, and motives by which you have been perſwaded, and if you would <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure God, produce order in your families, purſue the due edification of the Churches of God, prevent the Devils deſign, or put youth into a capacity to live with credit, or to die with comfort:</hi> Let me charge
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:119643:85"/>you in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt, as ſuperiors be conſtant in Catechizing, as inferiors be chearfull in being Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techized, ſhewing by your diligence in it the dignity of the exerciſe, your ſubmiſſion being a ſeal of the divine inſtitution of it; proclaiming unto all, that it is Gods ordinance to be continued in his Church.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:119643:85"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the ſigne of the Three Crowns, over againſt the great Conduit at the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>DR. <hi>Richard Sibbs</hi> his Commentary upon the Second Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> publiſhed for publick good by <hi>Tho. Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi> in <hi>Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>John Cotton</hi> his Expoſition on the Firſt Epiſtle of <hi>John,</hi> with Doctrines, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Uſes. in <hi>Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Journal or Diary of a thankful Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, wherein is contained directions for the right method of keeping and uſing, according to the rules of practiſe, a Day-book of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional and Politick, perſonal and private paſſages of Gods Providence, to help Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to thankfulneſs, and experience. By <hi>John Beadle</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Barn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cathechizing Gods Ordinance, or A
<pb facs="tcp:119643:86"/>ſhort Treatiſe concerning that Ancient, approved and ſoul edifying Ordinance of Catechiſme, by Mr. <hi>Zach. Crofton</hi> Miniſter of the word at <hi>Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tolphs</hi> without <hi>Algate, London;</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Curteous Reader.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THou mayeſt expect within a ſhort time to ſee publiſhed ſome new Pieces of Mr.</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Fenners, <hi>who was ſo famous when living, and his works (though he is dead) hath ſuch a ſweet (though ſilent) voice.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>T. P.</signed>
               </closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:119643:86"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
